<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<recipes>
    <recipe>
        <recipeTitle>Paneer Butter Masala Recipe (Paneer In Buttery Tomato Gravy)</recipeTitle>
        <prepTime>10
            minutes</prepTime>
        <blogContent>
            <span>Menu</span>
            <p>Dassana's Veg Recipes</p>
            <span>Search</span>
            <ul>Home
                Recipes
                About</ul>
            <li>Home</li>
            <li>Recipes</li>
            <li>About</li>
            <p>Home
                » Recipes » Paneer Recipes</p>
            <span>Home
                » Recipes » Paneer Recipes</span>
            <span>Home</span>
            <span>Home</span>
            <span>Home</span>
            <span>Recipes</span>
            <span>Paneer Recipes</span>
            <h1>Paneer Butter Masala Recipe (Paneer In Buttery Tomato Gravy)</h1>
            <p>By Dassana Amit
                Last Updated: October 31, 2022</p>
            <p>Gluten Free, Vegetarian
                4.92 from 367 votes • 568 Comments</p>
            <span>Gluten Free, Vegetarian</span>
            <span>4.92 from 367 votes</span>
            <span>4.92 from 367 votes</span>
            <span>4.92</span>
            <span>367</span>
            <span>Shares
                26k</span>
            <span>Shares</span>
            <span>Shares</span>
            <span>26k</span>
            <p>Paneer Butter Masala is one of India’s most popular paneer gravy recipes, and with
                good reason! Indian cottage cheese cubes are smothered in a creamy, lightly spiced
                tomato sauce that is downright delicious. With my video and step-by-step guide you
                can easily make this restaurant style Paneer Butter Masala recipe at home!</p>
            <p>Table of Contents</p>
            <li>About Paneer Butter Masala Recipe</li>
            <li>Ingredients You Need</li>
            <li>How to Make Paneer Butter Masala</li>
            <li>Expert Tips</li>
            <li>FAQs</li>
            <li>More Questions Answered</li>
            <li>Recipe Card</li>
            <h2>About Paneer Butter Masala Recipe</h2>
            <p>This Paneer Butter Masala recipe is a rich and creamy dish of paneer (Indian cottage
                cheese) in a tomato, butter and cashew sauce that is known here as “makhani gravy.”
                The acidity of the tomatoes and the sweetness of the cream make for a velvety,
                nearly addictive sauce.</p>
            <p>Also known as “Butter Paneer,” this yummy and popular vegetarian dish is derived from
                the recipe for Butter Chicken, a.k.a. Chicken Makhani, that I learned to make during
                my cooking school days. I know, I know, the thought of me cooking with meat sounds
                insane. It seems nearly a lifetime ago!</p>
            <p>With my easy, quick and delicious recipe you can prepare this Restaurant style Paneer
                Butter Masala at home. In fact, it’s so easy that you can make it on even busy
                weeknights! This simple dinner takes just 10 minutes of prep work and 30 minutes on
                the stove.</p>
            <p>My delicious Paneer Butter Masala recipe is one of the most popular recipes on the
                blog. It has been made and loved by hundreds of readers.</p>
            <p>Don’t just take my word for it, either. You can read the comments at the end of the
                post, which has a lot of positive feedback and reviews from our readers and fans.</p>
            <h2>Ingredients You Need</h2>
            <p>1. Ripe, red &amp; juicy tomatoes: Tomatoes are a key ingredient here and form the
                base of the makhani sauce. As such, it is important to choose good, ripe tomatoes
                that are sweet.</p>
            <p>If ripe tomatoes are not in season where you live, I suggest opting for using canned
                whole tomatoes that you blend instead.</p>
            <p>These canned tomatoes are picked at peak ripeness, and for whatever reason, the whole
                variety is generally much more flavorful than tomato purée.</p>
            <p>2. Raw Cashews: Yet another important ingredient for the gravy is cashews. The nuts
                impart a lovely creaminess and sheen in the dish, and the sweetness of the cashews
                help to balance the tanginess of the tomatoes.</p>
            <p>If you are nut free, please see my recipe for Paneer Makhani, which tastes quite
                similar but is made with just cream and no cashews.</p>
            <p>3. Cream: In addition to using cashew paste, this Butter Paneer recipe calls for
                cream to help thicken the sauce and add richness.</p>
            <p>If you are vegan, you can opt to use coconut cream instead, though you should note
                that the final flavor of the dish will be impacted a bit. You can also opt to omit
                the cream for a less rich gravy, too.</p>
            <p>4. Butter: The amount of butter that is added is just right in this paneer butter
                masala recipe. Butter makes the curry luxurious and, well… buttery.</p>
            <p>I don’t add a ton of butter here, so you don’t have to feel too guilty about it. Also
                note that you can go overboard by adding too much butter, so I recommend that you
                stick to the recipe.</p>
            <p>5. Paneer: The quality of your paneer can make or break your dish. What you want are
                succulent, soft paneer cubes gently coated with a smooth, buttery tomato sauce.</p>
            <p>Make sure to use either Homemade Paneer (which I believe is always the best option)
                or good quality store bought paneer. If you opt to use store bought, be sure to
                follow the instructions on the package before using.</p>
            <p>6. Spices &amp; Herbs: One reason this recipe is so great for weeknights is that the
                list of herbs and spices isn’t intimidatingly long. For that brilliant orange color,
                you need to add Kashmiri red chilli powder.</p>
            <p>If you don’t have any on hand, you can sub it with cayenne pepper or sweet paprika
                instead. You will also need garam masala powder. Kasuri methi, which are dried
                fenugreek leaves, also add good flavor.</p>
            <p>Just skip them if you do not have them. For garnish, fresh cilantro (coriander
                leaves) are added.</p>
            <span>Step-by-Step Guide</span>
            <h2>How to Make Paneer Butter Masala</h2>
            <p>You will have to do some light prep work before you begin making this delicious
                recipe. It starts with soaking your cashews, making tomato puree and blending soaked
                cashews.</p>
            <h3>Preparation</h3>
            <p>1. Soak 18 to 20 cashews in ⅓ cup hot water for 20 to 30 minutes.</p>
            <p>2. While the cashews are soaking, you can prep the other ingredients. It’s time for
                chopping tomatoes, chopping and preparing the ginger-garlic paste, and slicing
                paneer into cubes.</p>
            <p>3. To make the ginger garlic paste, crush a 1 inch piece of peeled ginger with 3 to 4
                small to medium-sized garlic cloves in a mortar &amp; pestle. Continue crushing
                until it is a semi-fine or fine paste. Keep aside.</p>
            <p>Note: Don’t add any water while crushing ginger &amp; garlic.</p>
            <p>4. After 20 to 30 minutes, drain the water and add the soaked cashews to a blender or
                mixer-grinder.</p>
            <p>Also, add 2 to 3 tablespoons fresh water (or as much as is required to blend to a
                fine paste).</p>
            <p>5. Blend to a smooth paste without any tiny bits or chunks of cashews. Remove the
                cashew paste from the blender and set it aside.</p>
            <p>6. In the same blender, add 2 cups of diced or roughly chopped tomatoes.</p>
            <p>Note: There’s no need to blanch the tomatoes or to wash the blender pitcher before
                blending.</p>
            <p>7. Blend to a smooth tomato puree. Set aside.</p>
            <p>Note: Don’t add any water while blending the tomatoes.</p>
            <h3>Make Tomato Gravy</h3>
            <p>8. Heat a thick bottomed pan or a heavy pan. Keep the heat to a low or medium-low.
                Add 2 tablespoons (or 3 to 4 tablespoons for a richer version) butter in a pan.
                Either salted or unsalted butter can be used.</p>
            <p>Tip: Alternatively, you can add 1 tablespoon oil + 1-2 tablespoons of butter to the
                pan. Adding oil prevents the butter from browning too quickly.</p>
            <p>9. Keep the the heat to a low. Add 1 medium-sized tej patta and fry for 2 to 3
                seconds, or until fragrant.</p>
            <p>10. Add the prepared crushed ginger-garlic or 1 teaspoon ready-made ginger-garlic
                paste.</p>
            <p>11. Sauté until the raw aroma of the ginger-garlic disappears, about 10 to 12
                seconds.</p>
            <p>12. Pour in the prepared tomato purée.</p>
            <p>Note: Be careful while adding the purée as it may splutter.</p>
            <p>13. Mix it very well with the butter.</p>
            <p>14. Begin to cook the tomato purée on a low to medium-low heat. Stir at intervals.</p>
            <p>15. The tomato purée mixture will start simmering.</p>
            <p>16. If the tomato purée splutters too much while cooking, then cover the pan partly
                with a lid or cover fully with a splatter guard (channi lid).</p>
            <p>17. Continue stirring occasionally.</p>
            <p>18. Simmer the purée for 5 to 6 minutes.</p>
            <p>19. Add 1 teaspoon Kashmiri red chili powder or deghi mirch.</p>
            <p>You can also opt to add just ½ teaspoon Kashmiri red chili powder, or ¼ – ½ teaspoon
                of cayenne, paprika or any other variety of red chilli powder that you prefer.</p>
            <p>20. Mix well and continue to stir and sauté the tomato purée.</p>
            <p>21. Sauté till the butter starts leaving the sides of the pan and the entire tomato
                purée mixture comes together as more of a thick paste.</p>
            <p>Note: This entire cooking/sautéing process takes about 14 to 17 minutes on a low to
                medium-low heat. Time will vary depending on the thickness of the pan, size, the
                intensity of flame etc.</p>
            <h3>Add Cashew Paste</h3>
            <p>22. Now add the prepared cashew paste.</p>
            <p>23. Mix the cashew paste very well with the cooked tomato puree and continue to stir
                and sauté on a low to medium-low heat.</p>
            <p>After adding cashew paste, be sure to continuously stir the gravy.</p>
            <p>24. Sauté until the cashew paste is cooked and the oil begins to leave the sides of
                the masala. The cashew will cook quickly, just around 3 to 4 minutes on a low heat.
                And don’t forget to keep on stirring non-stop!</p>
            <p>25. Next add 1.5 cups water.</p>
            <h3>Assemble Paneer Butter Masala</h3>
            <p>26. Mix the water very well with the tomato-cashew masala. If there are lumps, then
                break them with a spoon or use a wired whisk for mixing.</p>
            <p>27. Let the curry simmer and come to a boil on a low to medium-low heat. Stir
                occasionally.</p>
            <p>28. After 2 to 3 mins, add ginger julienne (about 1-inch ginger – cut in thin,
                matchstick-like strips). Reserve a few for garnishing. The curry will begin to
                thicken.</p>
            <p>29. After 3 to 4 minutes, add 1 or 2 slit green chiles.</p>
            <p>30. Also add salt to taste and, if necessary, ¼ to 1 teaspoon sugar depending on the
                sourness of the tomatoes.</p>
            <p>Tip: If you add cream, then you will need to add less sugar. You can also opt to omit
                sugar entirely if you prefer.</p>
            <p>31. Mix very well and simmer for a minute.</p>
            <p>32. After the gravy thickens to your desired consistency, then add the paneer cubes
                (200 or 250 grams).</p>
            <p>Tip: Keep in mind the consistency you want before you add paneer, as you will be
                cooking the paneer for just a few seconds, until it is warmed through. You can also
                fry the paneer and then add it once the gravy is to your liking.</p>
            <p>33. Stir and mix the paneer cubes gently in the gravy. You can switch off the heat at
                this point.</p>
            <p>Tip: If your paneer still tastes raw at this point, leave the heat on low until after
                you add the cream in step 35.</p>
            <p>34. Now quickly add 1 teaspoon crushed dry fenugreek leaves (kasuri methi leaves) and
                1 teaspoon garam masala to the gravy.</p>
            <p>Note: The addition of crushed dry fenugreek leaves gives a restaurant flavor to this
                curry, but it is optional and can be skipped.</p>
            <p>35. Next add 2 to 3 tablespoons of low-fat or light cream or 1 to 2 tablespoons of
                heavy whipping cream.</p>
            <p>36. Stir gently but well. If you haven’t yet, switch off the heat.</p>
            <p>37. Serve Paneer Butter Masala hot garnished with 1 to 2 tablespoons of chopped
                coriander leaves (cilantro) and the remaining ginger julienne. You can also drizzle
                some cream or dot with butter while serving. Enjoy!</p>
            <h3>What to eat with Paneer Butter Masala</h3>
            <li>Eat with the staple Indian bread roti: Paneer butter masala gravy has a slightly
                sweet taste and very mildly spiced. Thus making it an excellent gravy to go with
                roti or chapati.</li>
            <li>With other Indian breads: Another great combination for this dish is naan bread or
                tandoori roti or paratha or roomali roti or Malabar paratha.</li>
            <li>With rice: It also goes well with steamed basmati rice or jeera rice (cumin rice).</li>
            <h3>Ingredient Notes and Swaps</h3>
            <ul>Tomatoes: Since tomatoes are the key ingredient, make sure to use ripe, red and firm
                tomatoes with a slightly sweet taste. If ripe tomatoes aren’t in season, opt for
                canned instead.
                Paneer (Indian cottage cheese): Always use homemade Paneer if possible, or
                substitute a good quality, store-bought, fresh paneer. Honestly, it is best to make
                paneer at home and does not take much time.
                Butter: Use good quality butter. You can use either unsalted or salted, yellow or
                white butter so long as it is fresh and of good quality.
                Replacement for cashews: If you don’t have cashews, then the best alternative is
                almonds. Soak the almonds in hot water for 30 minutes, then peel them and blend to a
                fine consistency with little water. You can also go nut-free and make my Paneer
                Makhani recipe instead.
                Color: To get the bright orangish-red color that we associate with makhani gravy, it
                is best to use Kashmiri red chili powder or deghi mirch as your chili powder. Using
                deep red colored tomatoes also contributes to a lovely orange color in the gravy. I
                do not recommend using artificial food colors.</ul>
            <li>Tomatoes: Since tomatoes are the key ingredient, make sure to use ripe, red and firm
                tomatoes with a slightly sweet taste. If ripe tomatoes aren’t in season, opt for
                canned instead.</li>
            <li>Paneer (Indian cottage cheese): Always use homemade Paneer if possible, or
                substitute a good quality, store-bought, fresh paneer. Honestly, it is best to make
                paneer at home and does not take much time.</li>
            <li>Butter: Use good quality butter. You can use either unsalted or salted, yellow or
                white butter so long as it is fresh and of good quality.</li>
            <li>Replacement for cashews: If you don’t have cashews, then the best alternative is
                almonds. Soak the almonds in hot water for 30 minutes, then peel them and blend to a
                fine consistency with little water. You can also go nut-free and make my Paneer
                Makhani recipe instead.</li>
            <li>Color: To get the bright orangish-red color that we associate with makhani gravy, it
                is best to use Kashmiri red chili powder or deghi mirch as your chili powder. Using
                deep red colored tomatoes also contributes to a lovely orange color in the gravy. I
                do not recommend using artificial food colors.</li>
            <h3>Easy Swaps For a Vegan Version</h3>
            <p>If you are a vegan, don’t worry! You can easily substitute the dairy ingredients with
                vegan alternatives and still get a delicious dish.</p>
            <ul>Tofu: To make a vegan recipe, replace tofu, seitan, tempeh with paneer.
                Vegan Butter or Oil: Add a neutral-tasting oil or vegan butter, and feel free to
                skip cream altogether.
                Coconut Cream: You can also opt to use coconut cream, but please note that the
                flavors of coconut will be felt in the final dish if you do.</ul>
            <li>Tofu: To make a vegan recipe, replace tofu, seitan, tempeh with paneer.</li>
            <li>Vegan Butter or Oil: Add a neutral-tasting oil or vegan butter, and feel free to
                skip cream altogether.</li>
            <li>Coconut Cream: You can also opt to use coconut cream, but please note that the
                flavors of coconut will be felt in the final dish if you do.</li>
            <h2>Expert Tips</h2>
            <ul>Tomato Purée: Be sure that your tomatoes are puréed very well. If you want, you can
                also strain the tomato purée.
                Cooking Tomato Purée: The tomato purée has to be cooked really well. For a visual
                cue that you have cooked it well enough, the butter should leave sides of the
                sautéed tomato puree. If the tomato puree is not sautéed well, the raw flavor of
                tomatoes will be felt in the dish.
                Cashew Paste: To blend cashews to a fine consistency, you should soak them in hot
                water for 30 minutes. Also, be sure to use raw cashews rather than roasted.
                Taste and Flavor: If the gravy tastes tangy or sour, then balance it out with a bit
                of sugar (up to 1 teaspoon) or cream. Also, note that if you add cream then you will
                likely have to add less sugar in the gravy.
                Frying Paneer: You can fry the paneer cubes if you want and then add in the prepared
                gravy or sauce.</ul>
            <li>Tomato Purée: Be sure that your tomatoes are puréed very well. If you want, you can
                also strain the tomato purée.</li>
            <li>Cooking Tomato Purée: The tomato purée has to be cooked really well. For a visual
                cue that you have cooked it well enough, the butter should leave sides of the
                sautéed tomato puree. If the tomato puree is not sautéed well, the raw flavor of
                tomatoes will be felt in the dish.</li>
            <li>Cashew Paste: To blend cashews to a fine consistency, you should soak them in hot
                water for 30 minutes. Also, be sure to use raw cashews rather than roasted.</li>
            <li>Taste and Flavor: If the gravy tastes tangy or sour, then balance it out with a bit
                of sugar (up to 1 teaspoon) or cream. Also, note that if you add cream then you will
                likely have to add less sugar in the gravy.</li>
            <li>Frying Paneer: You can fry the paneer cubes if you want and then add in the prepared
                gravy or sauce.</li>
            <h2>FAQs</h2>
            <p>Onions are not traditional in makhani gravy and will change the taste of the final
                dish. But if you still want to add them, just add about ¼ to ⅓ cup finely chopped
                onions.

                You can also add ½ cup onion paste. Add paste after adding tej patta and then sauté
                the onion paste till light golden.</p>
            <p>In Indian recipes where cashews are ground to a paste, raw cashews are always used.</p>
            <p>Yes, you can use canned tomato purée, but add up to a teaspoon of sugar in the gravy
                if the purée is too tangy.

                Note: If you are using canned products, I suggest opting for canned whole tomatoes
                that you purée yourself for the best flavor.</p>
            <p>Yes, you can blanch tomatoes before puréeing them, but it is not necessary. If you
                prefer, you can also opt to strain the tomato purée.</p>
            <p>Yes this will reduce the cooking time, but the taste will be same.</p>
            <p>In the recipe, use tomatoes which are not very tangy or sour. The tomatoes should be
                ripe but firm. They should be red in color and not yellow or white.

                Roma tomatoes are a good choice. If you live in India, use the large salad tomatoes
                or larger sized tomatoes and not the small Indian desi variety of tomatoes.</p>
            <p>Just skip adding it.</p>
            <p>You can add milk powder, but you have to be careful as it makes the dish excessively
                sweet. I would suggest to add ½ tablespoon initially and do a taste check.

                If gravy is not creamy or sweet enough, then add an extra ¼ to ½ tablespoon, but
                avoid adding more than a total of 1 tablespoon. Do not add milk, as it may curdle
                from the acidity of tomatoes.</p>
            <p>Kasuri methi are dried fenugreek leaves. They are highly aromatic and give a subtle
                aroma in any dish. You can skip them or sub with a light pinch of ground fenugreek
                seed powder.</p>
            <p>Try adding some more cream and a bit more sugar. This will balance the sourness in
                the gravy.</p>
            <p>Honey becomes toxic when heated, so better to avoid it. Or you can add honey, when
                the paneer butter masala is warm. Don’t add when hot.</p>
            <p>You can use ghee (clarified butter) or neutral tasting oil.</p>
            <h2>More Questions Answered</h2>
            <p>What is the difference between Paneer Butter Masala and Paneer Tikka Masala?Paneer
                Butter Masala is a creamy and mildly sweet gravy made with butter, tomatoes,
                cashews, spices and paneer. Paneer Tikka Masala is a robust dish made with grilled
                yogurt marinated paneer cubes (called paneer tikka) in a spicy, robust tomato-onion
                gravy.</p>
            <p>What is Butter Paneer?
                Butter Paneer is another name for Paneer Butter Masala. They are one and the same
                dish.</p>
            <p>Why is my paneer rubbery?
                Paneer becomes rubbery and dense when overcooked. Try not to cook the cubes for a
                long time in a gravy or curry. Simply mix them with the gravy and switch off the
                heat once they are warmed through.</p>
            <p>Should you fry paneer before adding to curry?
                Yes, you can opt to fry the paneer cubes before you add them in the curry or gravy.
                You can either pan fry or shallow fry paneer cubes until light golden. Do not fry
                them for a long time – they become dense and rubbery when overcooked.</p>
            <p>Why does paneer break while cooking?
                If your homemade paneer has too much moisture, it will break and crumble while
                cooking.</p>
            <p>What can I substitute cashews with?
                You can use cashew butter (unsweetened) or add almonds. Soak almonds in hot water
                for 30 minutes. Remove the peels and blend to a smooth consistency in a blender or
                mixer. You can also use almond powder or almond meal.</p>
            <p>If you are nut free, I suggest you check out my recipe for Paneer Makhani, which has
                a similar flavor but is made without nuts.</p>
            <p>What can be used instead of cream in Paneer Butter Masala?
                Simply skip the cream in my paneer butter masala recipe. The cashews do give a
                creaminess to the gravy.</p>
            <p>More Paneer Recipes To Try!</p>
            <p>MODERATE • 40
                MINUTES
                MINS</p>
            <span>MODERATE</span>
            <span>40
                MINUTES
                MINS</span>
            <span>40
                MINUTES</span>
            <span>MINUTES</span>
            <span>MINS</span>
            <p>Paneer Recipes</p>
            <p>Palak Paneer Recipe (Spinach &amp; Paneer Cheese Curry)</p>
            <p>DIFFICULT • 1
                HOUR
                HR 30
                MINUTES
                MINS</p>
            <span>DIFFICULT</span>
            <span>1
                HOUR
                HR 30
                MINUTES
                MINS</span>
            <span>1
                HOUR</span>
            <span>HOUR</span>
            <span>HR</span>
            <span>30
                MINUTES</span>
            <span>MINUTES</span>
            <span>MINS</span>
            <p>Paneer Recipes</p>
            <p>Malai Kofta Recipe (Restaurant Style Paneer Kofta)</p>
            <p>MODERATE • 30
                MINUTES
                MINS</p>
            <span>MODERATE</span>
            <span>30
                MINUTES
                MINS</span>
            <span>30
                MINUTES</span>
            <span>MINUTES</span>
            <span>MINS</span>
            <p>Paneer Recipes</p>
            <p>Matar Paneer Recipe | Punjabi Mutter Paneer</p>
            <p>MODERATE • 2
                HOURS
                HRS</p>
            <span>MODERATE</span>
            <span>2
                HOURS
                HRS</span>
            <span>2
                HOURS</span>
            <span>HOURS</span>
            <span>HRS</span>
            <p>Paneer Recipes</p>
            <p>Paneer Tikka Masala Recipe – Restaurant Style Delight</p>
            <p>Please be sure to rate the recipe in the recipe card or leave a comment below if you
                have made it. For more vegetarian inspirations, Sign Up for my emails or follow me
                on Instagram, Youtube, Facebook, Pinterest or Twitter.</p>
            <h2>Paneer Butter Masala Recipe (Restaurant Style)</h2>
            <p>By Dassana Amit</p>
            <span>Paneer Butter Masala Recipe is one of India’s most popular paneer preparation.
                This restaurant style recipe with soft paneer cubes dunked in a creamy, lightly
                spiced tomato sauce or gravy is a best one that I have been making for a long time.
                This rich dish is best served with roti or chapati, paratha, naan or rumali roti.</span>
            <span>4.92</span>
            <span>367</span>
            <span>Prep Time</span>
            <span>10
                minutes
                mins</span>
            <span>10
                minutes</span>
            <span>minutes</span>
            <span>mins</span>
            <span>Cook Time</span>
            <span>30
                minutes
                mins</span>
            <span>30
                minutes</span>
            <span>minutes</span>
            <span>mins</span>
            <span>Total Time</span>
            <span>40
                minutes
                mins</span>
            <span>40
                minutes</span>
            <span>minutes</span>
            <span>mins</span>
            <span>Cuisine</span>
            <span>North Indian</span>
            <span>Course</span>
            <span>Main Course</span>
            <span>Diet</span>
            <span>Gluten Free, Vegetarian</span>
            <span>Difficulty Level</span>
            <span>Moderate</span>
            <p>Share</p>
            <span>Servings</span>
            <span>Units</span>
            <h3>Ingredients</h3>
            <ul>▢
                18 to 20 cashews – whole
                ▢
                ⅓ cup hot water – for soaking cashews</ul>
            <li>▢
                18 to 20 cashews – whole</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>18 to 20</span>
            <span>cashews</span>
            <span>– whole</span>
            <li>▢
                ⅓ cup hot water – for soaking cashews</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>⅓</span>
            <span>cup</span>
            <span>hot water</span>
            <span>– for soaking cashews</span>
            <ul>▢
                2 cups tomatoes – diced, or 300 grams tomatoes or 4 to 5 medium sized, pureed</ul>
            <li>▢
                2 cups tomatoes – diced, or 300 grams tomatoes or 4 to 5 medium sized, pureed</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>2</span>
            <span>cups</span>
            <span>tomatoes</span>
            <span>– diced, or 300 grams tomatoes or 4 to 5 medium sized, pureed</span>
            <ul>▢
                1 inch ginger – peeled and roughly chopped
                ▢
                3 to 4 garlic cloves – small to medium-sized, peeled</ul>
            <li>▢
                1 inch ginger – peeled and roughly chopped</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>1</span>
            <span>inch</span>
            <span>ginger</span>
            <span>– peeled and roughly chopped</span>
            <li>▢
                3 to 4 garlic cloves – small to medium-sized, peeled</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>3 to 4</span>
            <span>garlic cloves</span>
            <span>– small to medium-sized, peeled</span>
            <ul>▢
                2 tablespoons Butter or 1 tablespoon oil + 1 or 2 tablespoons butter
                ▢
                1 tej patta (Indian bay leaf), optional
                ▢
                ½ to 1 teaspoon kashmiri red chili powder or deghi mirch or ¼ to ½ teaspoon cayenne
                pepper or paprika
                ▢
                1.5 cups water or add as required
                ▢
                1 inch ginger – peeled and julienned, reserve a few for garnish
                ▢
                1 or 2 green chili – slit, reserve a few for garnish
                ▢
                200 to 250 grams Paneer (Indian cottage cheese) – cubed or diced
                ▢
                1 teaspoon dry fenugreek leaves (kasuri methi) – optional
                ▢
                ½ to 1 teaspoon Garam Masala or tandoori masala
                ▢
                2 to 3 tablespoons light cream or half &amp; half or 1 to 2 tablespoons heavy cream
                – optional
                ▢
                ¼ to 1 teaspoon sugar – optional, add as required depending on the sourness of the
                tomatoes
                ▢
                salt as required</ul>
            <li>▢
                2 tablespoons Butter or 1 tablespoon oil + 1 or 2 tablespoons butter</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>2</span>
            <span>tablespoons</span>
            <span>Butter</span>
            <span>or 1 tablespoon oil + 1 or 2 tablespoons butter</span>
            <li>▢
                1 tej patta (Indian bay leaf), optional</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>1</span>
            <span>tej patta</span>
            <span>(Indian bay leaf), optional</span>
            <li>▢
                ½ to 1 teaspoon kashmiri red chili powder or deghi mirch or ¼ to ½ teaspoon cayenne
                pepper or paprika</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>½ to 1</span>
            <span>teaspoon</span>
            <span>kashmiri red chili powder</span>
            <span>or deghi mirch or ¼ to ½ teaspoon cayenne pepper or paprika</span>
            <li>▢
                1.5 cups water or add as required</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>1.5</span>
            <span>cups</span>
            <span>water</span>
            <span>or add as required</span>
            <li>▢
                1 inch ginger – peeled and julienned, reserve a few for garnish</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>1</span>
            <span>inch</span>
            <span>ginger</span>
            <span>– peeled and julienned, reserve a few for garnish</span>
            <li>▢
                1 or 2 green chili – slit, reserve a few for garnish</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>1 or 2</span>
            <span>green chili</span>
            <span>– slit, reserve a few for garnish</span>
            <li>▢
                200 to 250 grams Paneer (Indian cottage cheese) – cubed or diced</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>200 to 250</span>
            <span>grams</span>
            <span>Paneer</span>
            <span>(Indian cottage cheese) – cubed or diced</span>
            <li>▢
                1 teaspoon dry fenugreek leaves (kasuri methi) – optional</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>1</span>
            <span>teaspoon</span>
            <span>dry fenugreek leaves</span>
            <span>(kasuri methi) – optional</span>
            <li>▢
                ½ to 1 teaspoon Garam Masala or tandoori masala</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>½ to 1</span>
            <span>teaspoon</span>
            <span>Garam Masala</span>
            <span>or tandoori masala</span>
            <li>▢
                2 to 3 tablespoons light cream or half &amp; half or 1 to 2 tablespoons heavy cream
                – optional</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>2 to 3</span>
            <span>tablespoons</span>
            <span>light cream</span>
            <span>or half &amp; half or 1 to 2 tablespoons heavy cream – optional</span>
            <li>▢
                ¼ to 1 teaspoon sugar – optional, add as required depending on the sourness of the
                tomatoes</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>¼ to 1</span>
            <span>teaspoon</span>
            <span>sugar</span>
            <span>– optional, add as required depending on the sourness of the tomatoes</span>
            <li>▢
                salt as required</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>salt</span>
            <span>as required</span>
            <ul>▢
                1 to 2 tablespoons coriander leaves – chopped, (cilantro) – optional
                ▢
                1 inch ginger – peeled and julienned
                ▢
                1 tablespoon light cream or 1 tablespoon heavy cream – optional
                ▢
                1 to 2 teaspoons Butter – optional</ul>
            <li>▢
                1 to 2 tablespoons coriander leaves – chopped, (cilantro) – optional</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>1 to 2</span>
            <span>tablespoons</span>
            <span>coriander leaves</span>
            <span>– chopped, (cilantro) – optional</span>
            <li>▢
                1 inch ginger – peeled and julienned</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>1</span>
            <span>inch</span>
            <span>ginger</span>
            <span>– peeled and julienned</span>
            <li>▢
                1 tablespoon light cream or 1 tablespoon heavy cream – optional</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>1</span>
            <span>tablespoon</span>
            <span>light cream</span>
            <span>or 1 tablespoon heavy cream – optional</span>
            <li>▢
                1 to 2 teaspoons Butter – optional</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>1 to 2</span>
            <span>teaspoons</span>
            <span>Butter</span>
            <span>– optional</span>
            <span>Cook Mode</span>
            <span>Prevent your screen from going dark while making the recipe</span>
            <h3>Instructions</h3>
            <ul>Soak cashews in a hot water for 20 to 30 minutes. When the cashews are soaking, you
                can prep the other ingredients like chopping tomatoes, preparing ginger-garlic
                paste, slicing paneer etc.
                Then drain and add the soaked cashews in a blender or mixer-grinder.
                Add 2 to 3 tablespoons water and blend to a smooth and fine paste without any tiny
                bits or chunks of cashews.
                In the same blender add the roughly chopped tomatoes. No need to blanch the tomatoes
                before blending.
                Blend to a smooth tomato puree. Set aside. Don’t add any water while blending the
                tomatoes.</ul>
            <li>Soak cashews in a hot water for 20 to 30 minutes. When the cashews are soaking, you
                can prep the other ingredients like chopping tomatoes, preparing ginger-garlic
                paste, slicing paneer etc.</li>
            <span>Soak cashews in a hot water for 20 to 30 minutes. When the cashews are soaking,
                you can prep the other ingredients like chopping tomatoes, preparing ginger-garlic
                paste, slicing paneer etc.</span>
            <li>Then drain and add the soaked cashews in a blender or mixer-grinder.</li>
            <span>Then drain and add the soaked cashews in a blender or mixer-grinder.</span>
            <li>Add 2 to 3 tablespoons water and blend to a smooth and fine paste without any tiny
                bits or chunks of cashews.</li>
            <span>Add 2 to 3 tablespoons water and blend to a smooth and fine paste without any tiny
                bits or chunks of cashews.</span>
            <li>In the same blender add the roughly chopped tomatoes. No need to blanch the tomatoes
                before blending.</li>
            <span>In the same blender add the roughly chopped tomatoes. No need to blanch the
                tomatoes before blending.</span>
            <li>Blend to a smooth tomato puree. Set aside. Don’t add any water while blending the
                tomatoes.</li>
            <span>Blend to a smooth tomato puree. Set aside. Don’t add any water while blending the
                tomatoes.</span>
            <ul>Melt butter in a pan on a low heat. Add tej patta and fry for 2 to 3 seconds or till
                the oil become fragrant.
                Add ginger-garlic paste and sauté for about 10 to 12 seconds till the raw aroma
                disappears.
                Add the tomato puree and stir well. Cook for 5 to 6 minutes stirring a few times.
                Next add kashmiri red chili powder and stir again. Continue to sauté till the oil
                starts to leave the sides of the tomato paste.
                The tomato paste will thicken considerably and will start coming together as one
                whole lump.
                Then add cashew paste and stir well. Sauté the cashew paste for a few minutes till
                the oil begins to leave the sides of the masala paste.
                The cashew paste will begin to cook fast. Approx 3 to 4 minutes on a low heat. So
                keep stirring non-stop.</ul>
            <li>Melt butter in a pan on a low heat. Add tej patta and fry for 2 to 3 seconds or till
                the oil become fragrant.</li>
            <span>Melt butter in a pan on a low heat. Add tej patta and fry for 2 to 3 seconds or
                till the oil become fragrant.</span>
            <li>Add ginger-garlic paste and sauté for about 10 to 12 seconds till the raw aroma
                disappears.</li>
            <span>Add ginger-garlic paste and sauté for about 10 to 12 seconds till the raw aroma
                disappears.</span>
            <li>Add the tomato puree and stir well. Cook for 5 to 6 minutes stirring a few times.</li>
            <span>Add the tomato puree and stir well. Cook for 5 to 6 minutes stirring a few times.</span>
            <li>Next add kashmiri red chili powder and stir again. Continue to sauté till the oil
                starts to leave the sides of the tomato paste.
                The tomato paste will thicken considerably and will start coming together as one
                whole lump.</li>
            <span>Next add kashmiri red chili powder and stir again. Continue to sauté till the oil
                starts to leave the sides of the tomato paste.</span>
            <span>The tomato paste will thicken considerably and will start coming together as one
                whole lump.</span>
            <li>Then add cashew paste and stir well. Sauté the cashew paste for a few minutes till
                the oil begins to leave the sides of the masala paste.</li>
            <span>Then add cashew paste and stir well. Sauté the cashew paste for a few minutes till
                the oil begins to leave the sides of the masala paste.</span>
            <li>The cashew paste will begin to cook fast. Approx 3 to 4 minutes on a low heat. So
                keep stirring non-stop.</li>
            <span>The cashew paste will begin to cook fast. Approx 3 to 4 minutes on a low heat. So
                keep stirring non-stop.</span>
            <ul>Add water and mix very well. Simmer on a low to medium-low heat.
                The curry will come to a boil.
                After 2 to 3 minutes of boiling, add ginger julienne. Reserve a few for garnishing.
                The curry will also begin to thicken.
                Add julienned ginger and green chillies, salt and sugar and simmer till the curry
                begins to thicken.
                After 3 to 4 minutes, add slit green chillies. also add salt as per taste and ½ to 1
                teaspoon sugar (optional).
                You can vary the sugar quantity from ¼ tsp to 1 teaspoon or more depending on the
                sourness of the tomatoes.
                Sugar is optional and you can skip it too. If you add cream, then you will need to
                add less sugar.
                Mix very well and simmer for a minute.
                After the gravy thickens to your desired consistency, then add the paneer cubes and
                stir gently. I keep the gravy to a medium consistency.
                After that add crushed kasuri methi (dry fenugreek leaves), garam masala and cream.
                Gently mix and then switch off the heat.</ul>
            <li>Add water and mix very well. Simmer on a low to medium-low heat.</li>
            <span>Add water and mix very well. Simmer on a low to medium-low heat.</span>
            <li>The curry will come to a boil.</li>
            <span>The curry will come to a boil.</span>
            <li>After 2 to 3 minutes of boiling, add ginger julienne. Reserve a few for garnishing.
                The curry will also begin to thicken.</li>
            <span>After 2 to 3 minutes of boiling, add ginger julienne. Reserve a few for
                garnishing. The curry will also begin to thicken.</span>
            <li>Add julienned ginger and green chillies, salt and sugar and simmer till the curry
                begins to thicken.</li>
            <li>After 3 to 4 minutes, add slit green chillies. also add salt as per taste and ½ to 1
                teaspoon sugar (optional).</li>
            <span>After 3 to 4 minutes, add slit green chillies. also add salt as per taste and ½ to
                1 teaspoon sugar (optional).</span>
            <li>You can vary the sugar quantity from ¼ tsp to 1 teaspoon or more depending on the
                sourness of the tomatoes.
                Sugar is optional and you can skip it too. If you add cream, then you will need to
                add less sugar.</li>
            <span>You can vary the sugar quantity from ¼ tsp to 1 teaspoon or more depending on the
                sourness of the tomatoes.</span>
            <span>Sugar is optional and you can skip it too. If you add cream, then you will need to
                add less sugar.</span>
            <li>Mix very well and simmer for a minute.</li>
            <span>Mix very well and simmer for a minute.</span>
            <li>After the gravy thickens to your desired consistency, then add the paneer cubes and
                stir gently. I keep the gravy to a medium consistency.</li>
            <span>After the gravy thickens to your desired consistency, then add the paneer cubes
                and stir gently. I keep the gravy to a medium consistency.</span>
            <li>After that add crushed kasuri methi (dry fenugreek leaves), garam masala and cream.
                Gently mix and then switch off the heat.</li>
            <span>After that add crushed kasuri methi (dry fenugreek leaves), garam masala and
                cream. Gently mix and then switch off the heat.</span>
            <ul>Garnish the curry with coriander leaves and ginger julienne.
                You can even dot the gravy with some butter or drizzle some cream.
                Serve Paneer Butter Masala hot with plain naan, garlic naan, roti, paratha or
                steamed basmati or jeera rice or even peas pulao.
                Side accompaniments can be an onion-cucumber salad or some pickle. Also serve some
                lemon wedges by the side.</ul>
            <li>Garnish the curry with coriander leaves and ginger julienne.</li>
            <span>Garnish the curry with coriander leaves and ginger julienne.</span>
            <li>You can even dot the gravy with some butter or drizzle some cream.</li>
            <span>You can even dot the gravy with some butter or drizzle some cream.</span>
            <li>Serve Paneer Butter Masala hot with plain naan, garlic naan, roti, paratha or
                steamed basmati or jeera rice or even peas pulao.</li>
            <span>Serve Paneer Butter Masala hot with plain naan, garlic naan, roti, paratha or
                steamed basmati or jeera rice or even peas pulao.</span>
            <li>Side accompaniments can be an onion-cucumber salad or some pickle. Also serve some
                lemon wedges by the side.</li>
            <span>Side accompaniments can be an onion-cucumber salad or some pickle. Also serve some
                lemon wedges by the side.</span>
            <h3>Video</h3>
            <h3>Notes</h3>
            <li>Butter: Use good quality butter. You can add both unsalted or salted butter. Also
                both yellow butter or white butter can be added.</li>
            <li>Tomatoes: It is best to use fresh, ripe red tomatoes. Add tomatoes which have
                sweet-tangy taste. Do not add tomatoes which are too sour or tart.</li>
            <li>Tomato puree: Blend the tomatoes to a smooth puree. If you want you can strain the
                tomato puree also.</li>
            <li>Sautéing tomato puree: The tomato puree has to be cooked and sautéed very well. Oil
                or butter should leave sides of the cooked tomato puree so that the raw flavor of
                tomatoes is not felt in the dish.</li>
            <li>Paneer: Best to use homemade soft paneer or a good quality store brought fresh
                paneer</li>
            <li>Cream: The amount of cream can be adjusted as per your taste.</li>
            <li>Cashew paste: To blend cashews to a fine consistency, it is better to soak them in
                hot water for 20 to 30 minutes. Use a good blender to get a smooth creamy cashew
                paste.</li>
            <li>Replacing cashews: If you don’t have cashews then add almonds. Blanch the almonds in
                hot water for 30 minutes. Then peel and blend them till smooth with some water.</li>
            <li>Sugar: Addition of sugar depends upon your taste as well as the tanginess present in
                the tomatoes. So add as per taste. If you add cream then you might have to add less
                sugar.</li>
            <li>Taste and flavor: If the butter paneer masala gravy tastes tangy or sour, then to
                balance the sour taste you can add a bit of sugar or cream. But do not add too much
                sugar as then the gravy becomes too sweet. Also, do note if you add cream then you
                might have to add less sugar in the sauce or gravy.</li>
            <li>Color: To get the bright orangish-red color, its best to use kashmiri red chilli
                powder or deghi mirch instead of artificial food colors. Using deep red colored
                tomatoes also contribute to a lovely orange color in the gravy.</li>
            <li>Frying paneer (optional): You can fry the paneer cubes if you want and then add in
                the prepared sauce or gravy.</li>
            <h3>Nutrition Info (Approximate Values)</h3>
            <span>Calories 307</span>
            <span>Calories from Fat 243</span>
            <span>% Daily Value*</span>
            <span>Fat 27g</span>
            <span>42%</span>
            <span>Saturated Fat 15g</span>
            <span>94%</span>
            <span>Cholesterol 66mg</span>
            <span>22%</span>
            <span>Sodium 493mg</span>
            <span>21%</span>
            <span>Potassium 221mg</span>
            <span>6%</span>
            <span>Carbohydrates 9g</span>
            <span>3%</span>
            <span>Fiber 2g</span>
            <span>8%</span>
            <span>Sugar 4g</span>
            <span>4%</span>
            <span>Protein 9g</span>
            <span>18%</span>
            <span>Vitamin A 1066IU</span>
            <span>21%</span>
            <span>Vitamin B1 (Thiamine) 1mg</span>
            <span>67%</span>
            <span>Vitamin B2 (Riboflavin) 1mg</span>
            <span>59%</span>
            <span>Vitamin B3 (Niacin) 1mg</span>
            <span>5%</span>
            <span>Vitamin B6 1mg</span>
            <span>50%</span>
            <span>Vitamin C 14mg</span>
            <span>17%</span>
            <span>Vitamin D 1µg</span>
            <span>7%</span>
            <span>Vitamin E 1mg</span>
            <span>7%</span>
            <span>Vitamin K 9µg</span>
            <span>9%</span>
            <span>Calcium 255mg</span>
            <span>26%</span>
            <span>Vitamin B9 (Folate) 13µg</span>
            <span>3%</span>
            <span>Iron 1mg</span>
            <span>6%</span>
            <span>Magnesium 28mg</span>
            <span>7%</span>
            <span>Phosphorus 63mg</span>
            <span>6%</span>
            <span>Zinc 1mg</span>
            <span>7%</span>
            <p>Like What You See?</p>
            <p>Stay up to date with new recipes and ideas.</p>
            <ul>Signup
                Subscribe
                Join
                Follow</ul>
            <li>Signup</li>
            <li>Subscribe</li>
            <li>Join</li>
            <li>Follow</li>
            <p>This Paneer Butter Masala recipe post from the archives was first published in April
                2013. It has been updated and republished on October 2022.</p>
            <p>Share This Recipe:</p>
            <span>Shares
                26k</span>
            <span>Shares</span>
            <span>Shares</span>
            <span>26k</span>
            <p>Meet Dassana</p>
            <p>Welcome to Dassana's Veg Recipes. I share vegetarian recipes from India &amp; around
                the World. Having been cooking for decades and with a professional background in
                cooking &amp; baking, I help you to make your cooking journey easier with my tried
                and tested recipes showcased with step by step photos &amp; plenty of tips &amp;
                suggestions.</p>
            <p>Comments are closed.</p>
            <h2>568 Comments</h2>
            <li>Opio
                All your recipes are amazing 👏
                Dassana Amit
                Thanks a lot.</li>
            <p>All your recipes are amazing 👏</p>
            <li>Dassana Amit
                Thanks a lot.</li>
            <p>Thanks a lot.</p>
            <li>Damayanti Anand
                Very good! 👌🏽✨
                Dassana Amit
                Thank you.</li>
            <p>Very good! 👌🏽✨</p>
            <li>Dassana Amit
                Thank you.</li>
            <p>Thank you.</p>
            <li>Paula
                Hi Dassana,
                Would you recommend preparing the sauce the night before and then heating the sauce
                and adding the paneer the next day to save time when hosting?
                Thank you
                Dassana Amit
                Yes of course you can do that. Prepare the sauce and refrigerate it. Just don’t add
                the cream, dry fenugreek leaves, garam masala powder. You add these three
                ingredients when you add the paneer.</li>
            <p>Hi Dassana,</p>
            <p>Would you recommend preparing the sauce the night before and then heating the sauce
                and adding the paneer the next day to save time when hosting?</p>
            <p>Thank you</p>
            <li>Dassana Amit
                Yes of course you can do that. Prepare the sauce and refrigerate it. Just don’t add
                the cream, dry fenugreek leaves, garam masala powder. You add these three
                ingredients when you add the paneer.</li>
            <p>Yes of course you can do that. Prepare the sauce and refrigerate it. Just don’t add
                the cream, dry fenugreek leaves, garam masala powder. You add these three
                ingredients when you add the paneer.</p>
            <li>Elena
                What a delicious dish, my daughter loved it so much that she asked me to make it
                again.
                Thank you so much 🙏🏽
                Dassana Amit
                Happy to hear! Thanks for the lovely feedback and the rating as well.</li>
            <p>What a delicious dish, my daughter loved it so much that she asked me to make it
                again.</p>
            <p>Thank you so much 🙏🏽</p>
            <li>Dassana Amit
                Happy to hear! Thanks for the lovely feedback and the rating as well.</li>
            <p>Happy to hear! Thanks for the lovely feedback and the rating as well.</p>
            <p>See More Comments</p>
            <p>As Seen In:</p>
            <ul>Recipe Glossary
                Press &amp; Media
                Privacy Policy
                Terms &amp; Conditions
                Accessibility Statement</ul>
            <li>Recipe Glossary</li>
            <li>Press &amp; Media</li>
            <li>Privacy Policy</li>
            <li>Terms &amp; Conditions</li>
            <li>Accessibility Statement</li>
            <p>Facebook
                YouTube
                Pinterest
                Twitter
                Instagram</p>
            <span>Facebook</span>
            <span>YouTube</span>
            <span>Pinterest</span>
            <span>Twitter</span>
            <span>Instagram</span>
            <p>© Dassana’s Veg Recipes 2009-2023</p>
        </blogContent>
    </recipe>
    <recipe>
        <recipeTitle>Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls Recipe With Four Pepper Cheese Dip</recipeTitle>
        <prepTime>Prep in
            60 M</prepTime>
        <blogContent>
            <span>×</span>
            <ul>Recipes
                World Recipes
                Continental Party Appetizer &amp; Starter Recipes
                Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls Recipe With Four Pepper Cheese Dip</ul>
            <li>Recipes</li>
            <span>Recipes</span>
            <li>World Recipes</li>
            <span>World Recipes</span>
            <li>Continental Party Appetizer &amp; Starter Recipes</li>
            <span>Continental Party Appetizer &amp; Starter Recipes</span>
            <li>Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls Recipe With Four Pepper Cheese Dip</li>
            <span>Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls Recipe With Four Pepper Cheese Dip</span>
            <h1>Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls Recipe With Four Pepper Cheese Dip</h1>
            <p>Crunchy, oozing with cheese and gently spiced with jalapeno these golden Jalapeno
                Potato Cheese Balls are a perfect appetizer for any party or a great evening snack.
                Serve it with Four pepper cheese spread by the side and we are sure you and your
                family with fall in love with these cheesy potato goodness.</p>
            <span>In association with Britannia Cheese</span>
            <span>Archana Doshi</span>
            <span>On Tuesday, 30 April 2019 10:00</span>
            <span>On</span>
            <span>4419 ratings.</span>
            <span>Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls Recipe is a simple recipe made with mashed potatoes,
                cheese cubes, jalapeno and parsley. The potato cheese mix is made into balls, dunked
                in an egg mixture and then rolled into bread crumbs. Then these Jalapeno Potato
                Cheese Balls are pan fried in a paniyaram pan till they are nice and golden brown in
                colour.
                You can use any leftover mashed potato mix as well for making this recipe. It is one
                of the tastiest and easiest party appetizer you can make as the Jalapeno Potato
                Cheese Balls can be refrigerated and fried whenever you require.
                Serve Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls as a party appetizer with Four Pepper Cheese Dip
                and a party meal of Classic Caesar Salad , Pumpkin Stew With Chickpeas and Pistachio
                &amp; Cranberry Broken Wheat Pilaf.
                Try our other similar party appetizer:
                High Protein Spinach &amp; Soy Bites Recipe
                Fennel Potato Croquettes With Paneer Recipe
                Spinach And Sweet Potato Bombs Recipe</span>
            <p>Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls Recipe is a simple recipe made with mashed potatoes,
                cheese cubes, jalapeno and parsley. The potato cheese mix is made into balls, dunked
                in an egg mixture and then rolled into bread crumbs. Then these Jalapeno Potato
                Cheese Balls are pan fried in a paniyaram pan till they are nice and golden brown in
                colour.</p>
            <p>You can use any leftover mashed potato mix as well for making this recipe. It is one
                of the tastiest and easiest party appetizer you can make as the Jalapeno Potato
                Cheese Balls can be refrigerated and fried whenever you require.</p>
            <p>Serve Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls as a party appetizer with Four Pepper Cheese Dip
                and a party meal of Classic Caesar Salad , Pumpkin Stew With Chickpeas and Pistachio
                &amp; Cranberry Broken Wheat Pilaf.</p>
            <p>Try our other similar party appetizer:</p>
            <li>High Protein Spinach &amp; Soy Bites Recipe</li>
            <li>Fennel Potato Croquettes With Paneer Recipe</li>
            <li>Spinach And Sweet Potato Bombs Recipe</li>
            <span>Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls Recipe With Four Pepper Cheese Dip Video</span>
            <span>Continental</span>
            <span>Appetizer</span>
            <span>Vegetarian</span>
            <span>Prep in
                60 M</span>
            <p>60 M</p>
            <span>Cooks in
                10 M</span>
            <p>10 M</p>
            <span>Total in
                70 M</span>
            <p>70 M</p>
            <span>Makes:
                4 Servings</span>
            <p>4 Servings</p>
            <h2>Ingredients</h2>
            <ul>2 cups Potatoes (Aloo) , mashed &amp; refrigerated
                6 Britannia Cheese Cubes , cut into small pieces
                4 cloves Garlic , finely chopped
                2 Pickled Jalapenos , finely chopped
                3 sprig Parsley leaves , finely chopped
                2 Whole Eggs , whisked
                1 cup Whole Wheat Bread crumbs
                1 teaspoon Mixed Herbs (Dried)
                Salt , to taste
                Oil , as required
                For the Four Pepper Cheese Dip
                3 tablespoons Britannia Cheese Spread - Four Pepper Tango
                3 tablespoons Hung Curd (Greek Yogurt)
                2 sprig Parsley leaves , finely chopped
                Salt , to taste</ul>
            <li>2 cups Potatoes (Aloo) , mashed &amp; refrigerated</li>
            <span>Potatoes (Aloo)</span>
            <li>6 Britannia Cheese Cubes , cut into small pieces</li>
            <span>Britannia Cheese Cubes</span>
            <li>4 cloves Garlic , finely chopped</li>
            <span>Garlic</span>
            <li>2 Pickled Jalapenos , finely chopped</li>
            <span>Pickled Jalapenos</span>
            <li>3 sprig Parsley leaves , finely chopped</li>
            <span>Parsley leaves</span>
            <li>2 Whole Eggs , whisked</li>
            <span>Whole Eggs</span>
            <li>1 cup Whole Wheat Bread crumbs</li>
            <span>Whole Wheat Bread crumbs</span>
            <li>1 teaspoon Mixed Herbs (Dried)</li>
            <span>Mixed Herbs (Dried)</span>
            <li>Salt , to taste</li>
            <span>Salt</span>
            <li>Oil , as required</li>
            <span>Oil</span>
            <li>3 tablespoons Britannia Cheese Spread - Four Pepper Tango</li>
            <span>Britannia Cheese Spread - Four Pepper Tango</span>
            <li>3 tablespoons Hung Curd (Greek Yogurt)</li>
            <span>Hung Curd (Greek Yogurt)</span>
            <li>2 sprig Parsley leaves , finely chopped</li>
            <span>Parsley leaves</span>
            <li>Salt , to taste</li>
            <span>Salt</span>
            <h2>How to make Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls Recipe With Four Pepper Cheese Dip</h2>
            <li>To begin making Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls Recipe combine the refrigerated mashed
                potatoes, jalapenos, parsley and salt to taste .</li>
            <p>To begin making Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls Recipe combine the refrigerated mashed
                potatoes, jalapenos, parsley and salt to taste .</p>
            <li>Shape the mix into ping pong size balls. Flatten the balls and add the chopped
                britannia cheese cubes in the center and then fold to make a ball again.</li>
            <p>Shape the mix into ping pong size balls. Flatten the balls and add the chopped
                britannia cheese cubes in the center and then fold to make a ball again.</p>
            <li>Refrigerate the Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls for 30 minutes.</li>
            <p>Refrigerate the Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls for 30 minutes.</p>
            <li>Mix the herbs with the bread crumbs in a plate and keep aside.</li>
            <p>Mix the herbs with the bread crumbs in a plate and keep aside.</p>
            <li>After 30 minutes remove the potato cheese balls from the fridge. Dip the chilled
                Potato Cheese Balls into whisked egg and roll over the herbed bread crumbs. Make all
                the balls and keep aside.</li>
            <p>After 30 minutes remove the potato cheese balls from the fridge. Dip the chilled
                Potato Cheese Balls into whisked egg and roll over the herbed bread crumbs. Make all
                the balls and keep aside.</p>
            <li>Now heat a kuzhi paniyaram pan with little oil in each cavity. Place the Jalapeno
                Potato Cheese Balls in the pan's cavities; drizzle the Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls
                with a little oil and pan fry them until golden brown on both sides.</li>
            <p>Now heat a kuzhi paniyaram pan with little oil in each cavity. Place the Jalapeno
                Potato Cheese Balls in the pan's cavities; drizzle the Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls
                with a little oil and pan fry them until golden brown on both sides.</p>
            <li>Once done remove the Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls onto an oil absorbent paper and
                serve hot.</li>
            <p>Once done remove the Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls onto an oil absorbent paper and
                serve hot.</p>
            <li>Combine Four pepper tango cheese spread, hung curd, salt and parsley in a bowl.
                Whisk it up well to combine all the ingredients together.</li>
            <p>Combine Four pepper tango cheese spread, hung curd, salt and parsley in a bowl. Whisk
                it up well to combine all the ingredients together.</p>
            <li>Transfer into a dip bowl and serve.</li>
            <p>Transfer into a dip bowl and serve.</p>
            <li>Serve Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls as a party appetizer with Four Pepper Cheese Dip
                and a party meal of Classic Caesar Salad , Pumpkin Stew With Chickpeas and Pistachio
                &amp; Cranberry Broken Wheat Pilaf.</li>
            <p>Serve Jalapeno Potato Cheese Balls as a party appetizer with Four Pepper Cheese Dip
                and a party meal of Classic Caesar Salad , Pumpkin Stew With Chickpeas and Pistachio
                &amp; Cranberry Broken Wheat Pilaf.</p>
            <span>Published in Continental Party Appetizer &amp; Starter Recipes</span>
            <ul>Party Food Recipes Vegetarian Recipes Tea Party Recipes Party Starter &amp;
                Appetizer Recipes Cheese Recipes Birthday Party Recipes</ul>
            <li>Party Food Recipes</li>
            <li>Vegetarian Recipes</li>
            <li>Tea Party Recipes</li>
            <li>Party Starter &amp; Appetizer Recipes</li>
            <li>Cheese Recipes</li>
            <li>Birthday Party Recipes</li>
            <span>Last Modified On Saturday, 18 November 2023 05:30</span>
            <ul>Vegetarian Thai Green Curry Recipe
                By Archana Doshi
                Homemade Macaroni And Cheese Recipe
                By Divya Shivaraman
                Sarson Ka Saag Recipe - Classic North Indian Saag Recipe
                By Archana Doshi
                Chicken Momos Recipe -Delicious Steamed Chicken Dumplings
                By Archana's Kitchen</ul>
            <li>Vegetarian Thai Green Curry Recipe
                By Archana Doshi</li>
            <span>By Archana Doshi</span>
            <li>Homemade Macaroni And Cheese Recipe
                By Divya Shivaraman</li>
            <span>By Divya Shivaraman</span>
            <li>Sarson Ka Saag Recipe - Classic North Indian Saag Recipe
                By Archana Doshi</li>
            <span>By Archana Doshi</span>
            <li>Chicken Momos Recipe -Delicious Steamed Chicken Dumplings
                By Archana's Kitchen</li>
            <span>By Archana's Kitchen</span>
            <ul>Karnataka Style Sandige Huli Recipe (Toor dal dumplings in Gravy Recipe)
                By Archana's Kitchen
                Andhra Style Palakura Pappu Recipe (Spinach Dal Recipe)
                By Archana's Kitchen
                Oatmeal Pancake Recipe With Orange
                By Archana Doshi
                Roasted Vegetables With Tahini Sauce Recipe
                By Archana's Kitchen
                Lilve Ki Sabzi Recipe (Green Chickpea Curry)
                By Pooja Thakur
                Chettinad Style Pepper Mushroom Recipe
                By Nithya Anantham</ul>
            <li>Karnataka Style Sandige Huli Recipe (Toor dal dumplings in Gravy Recipe)
                By Archana's Kitchen</li>
            <span>By Archana's Kitchen</span>
            <li>Andhra Style Palakura Pappu Recipe (Spinach Dal Recipe)
                By Archana's Kitchen</li>
            <span>By Archana's Kitchen</span>
            <li>Oatmeal Pancake Recipe With Orange
                By Archana Doshi</li>
            <span>By Archana Doshi</span>
            <li>Roasted Vegetables With Tahini Sauce Recipe
                By Archana's Kitchen</li>
            <span>By Archana's Kitchen</span>
            <li>Lilve Ki Sabzi Recipe (Green Chickpea Curry)
                By Pooja Thakur</li>
            <span>By Pooja Thakur</span>
            <li>Chettinad Style Pepper Mushroom Recipe
                By Nithya Anantham</li>
            <span>By Nithya Anantham</span>
            <ul>Andhra Pepper Chicken Recipe - Dry Restaurant Style Pepper Chicken
                By Archana Doshi
                Dhaba Mutton Recipe-Spicy Mutton Gravy
                By Pooja Thakur
                Mangalorean Chicken Ghee Roast Recipe
                By Archana's Kitchen
                Quick And Simple Egg Curry Recipe
                By Archana Doshi
                Kerala Egg Roast Masala Recipe
                By Archana Doshi
                Hariyali Chicken Tikka Recipe
                By Archana's Kitchen</ul>
            <li>Andhra Pepper Chicken Recipe - Dry Restaurant Style Pepper Chicken
                By Archana Doshi</li>
            <span>By Archana Doshi</span>
            <li>Dhaba Mutton Recipe-Spicy Mutton Gravy
                By Pooja Thakur</li>
            <span>By Pooja Thakur</span>
            <li>Mangalorean Chicken Ghee Roast Recipe
                By Archana's Kitchen</li>
            <span>By Archana's Kitchen</span>
            <li>Quick And Simple Egg Curry Recipe
                By Archana Doshi</li>
            <span>By Archana Doshi</span>
            <li>Kerala Egg Roast Masala Recipe
                By Archana Doshi</li>
            <span>By Archana Doshi</span>
            <li>Hariyali Chicken Tikka Recipe
                By Archana's Kitchen</li>
            <span>By Archana's Kitchen</span>
            <ul>Punjabi Style Tinda Sabzi Recipe
                By Madhuli Ajay
                Spicy Baby Potatoes Recipe
                By Shaheen Ali
                Baingan Tamatar Sabzi - Brinjal/ Eggplant Masala Recipe
                By Archana Doshi
                Aloo Simla Mirch Ki Sabzi Recipe - Aloo &amp; Capsicum Sabzi
                By Archana Doshi</ul>
            <li>Punjabi Style Tinda Sabzi Recipe
                By Madhuli Ajay</li>
            <span>By Madhuli Ajay</span>
            <li>Spicy Baby Potatoes Recipe
                By Shaheen Ali</li>
            <span>By Shaheen Ali</span>
            <li>Baingan Tamatar Sabzi - Brinjal/ Eggplant Masala Recipe
                By Archana Doshi</li>
            <span>By Archana Doshi</span>
            <li>Aloo Simla Mirch Ki Sabzi Recipe - Aloo &amp; Capsicum Sabzi
                By Archana Doshi</li>
            <span>By Archana Doshi</span>
            <ul>Mission,Vision &amp; Values
                Archana's Kitchen Team
                Careers
                Terms &amp; Conditions
                Privacy Policy
                © Archana's Online Media &amp; Publishing Services LLP</ul>
            <li>Mission,Vision &amp; Values</li>
            <li>Archana's Kitchen Team</li>
            <li>Careers</li>
            <li>Terms &amp; Conditions</li>
            <li>Privacy Policy</li>
            <li>© Archana's Online Media &amp; Publishing Services LLP</li>
            <span>© Archana's Online Media &amp; Publishing Services LLP</span>
            <ul>About Us
                Contact Us
                Clients
                Brands
                Press &amp; Media</ul>
            <li>About Us</li>
            <li>Contact Us</li>
            <li>Clients</li>
            <li>Brands</li>
            <li>Press &amp; Media</li>
        </blogContent>
    </recipe>
    <recipe>
        <recipeTitle>Paneer Butter Masala Recipe</recipeTitle>
        <prepTime>15
            minutes</prepTime>
        <blogContent>
            <span>Home &gt;&gt; Recipes &gt;&gt; North Indian</span>
            <span>Home</span>
            <span>Recipes</span>
            <span>North Indian</span>
            <h1>Paneer Butter Masala Recipe</h1>
            <p>By Swasthi on July 5, 2023, Comments, Jump to Recipe</p>
            <span>17K</span>
            <span>33K</span>
            <span>50K
                SHARES</span>
            <span>SHARES</span>
            <p>Paneer Butter Masala Recipe – Learn to make the best restaurant style Paneer Butter
                Masala at home. Isn’t it fun to recreate restaurant style dishes at home? Years ago,
                I found this BEST Paneer Butter Masala recipe in one of the cookbooks in a library.
                I tried it, tweaked it, then made this for years &amp; my entire family got hooked
                to it. It’s creamy, flavorful &amp; tastes super delicious!! It goes so well with
                Butter naan, roti, Chapati, plain fluffy Basmati Rice or Jeera Rice.</p>
            <p>I love simple recipes and easy cooking that calls fewer ingredients and fewer steps
                to follow. This restaurant style paneer butter masala recipe is always a winner for
                its simplicity &amp; amazing taste. So what is it?</p>
            <h2>About Paneer Butter Masala</h2>
            <span>About Paneer Butter Masala</span>
            <p>Paneer Butter Masala, also known as butter paneer is a rich &amp; creamy curry made
                with paneer, spices, onions, tomatoes, cashews and butter. As the name denotes, the
                curry is cooked in butter which imparts it’s characteristic buttery flavor to the
                dish.</p>
            <p>It is one of the most popular dishes in Indian restaurants similar to kadai paneer,
                Palak Paneer, Matar Paneer and Malai Kofta.</p>
            <p>This paneer butter masala is a curry lover’s dream!! Soft paneer dunked in a creamy,
                silky, super flavourful and delicious curry. My easy recipe will help you make the
                best butter paneer that tastes better than anything from a restaurant. Make this
                once and I am sure you will never order it in a restaurant.</p>
            <p>This is my go-to butter masala recipe. I published it on my blog 6 years ago &amp;
                after making it countless times, I decided to update my post with more tips,
                substitutes &amp; instant pot instructions which I have tried.</p>
            <span>hide</span>
            <span>1</span>
            <span>About Paneer Butter Masala</span>
            <span>2</span>
            <span>How to Make Paneer Butter Masala (Stepwise Pics)</span>
            <span>3</span>
            <span>Serving Suggestions</span>
            <span>4</span>
            <span>Pro Tips</span>
            <span>5</span>
            <span>Ingredients and substitutes</span>
            <span>6</span>
            <span>Instant pot Butter Paneer</span>
            <span>7</span>
            <span>Faqs</span>
            <span>8</span>
            <span>Recipe Card</span>
            <p>This recipe uses only pantry staples and does not need any fancy ingredients except
                for cream. I have also mentioned the substitutes for some ingredients.</p>
            <p>To make paneer butter masala, firstly onions, tomatoes &amp; cashews are sauteed with
                spices. Then these are blended to a silky smooth puree which forms the curry base.
                This is further simmered with butter &amp; spices to make the butter masala.</p>
            <p>Lastly cubed paneer is added to it along with the cream which makes it creamy &amp;
                amazingly delicious. Truly, a restaurant kind of paneer dish is ready in just 30 to
                40 minutes!</p>
            <p>More Paneer Recipes
                Paneer Pasanda
                Dhaba Paneer Curry
                Paneer tikka masala
                Paneer lababdar
                Kadai paneer
                Shahi paneer</p>
            <h2>How to Make Paneer Butter Masala (Stepwise Pics)</h2>
            <span>How to Make Paneer Butter Masala (Stepwise Pics)</span>
            <h3>Prepare the gravy</h3>
            <p>1. This step is optional and if you think your store bought paneer becomes hard after
                cooking you can follow this step &amp; don’t need to do it if using Homemade Paneer.
                Pour 2 cups of hot water to a bowl. Add 200 to 250 grams paneer cubes &amp; rest for
                about 15 to 20 mins. Later drain the water and set aside.</p>
            <p>2. Pour 1 tablespoon oil to a hot pan. Add 2 green cardamoms &amp; 1 cup cubed
                onions. Saute them on a medium flame till they turn transparent or lightly pink in
                color. This takes just 4 minutes.</p>
            <p>(Tip: If you do not have ginger garlic paste you may add the ¾ inch ginger (peeled
                &amp; chopped) and 3 medium garlic cloves here.)</p>
            <p>3. Next add the following:</p>
            <ul>1½ cups finely chopped tomatoes
                ¾ teaspoon salt. Again saute for 2 to 3 minutes. Then cover the pan and cook till
                mushy.</ul>
            <li>1½ cups finely chopped tomatoes</li>
            <li>¾ teaspoon salt. Again saute for 2 to 3 minutes. Then cover the pan and cook till
                mushy.</li>
            <p>4. When the tomatoes and onions are completely soft cooked &amp; mushy, add the
                following:</p>
            <ul>¾ to 1 teaspoon Kashmiri red chili powder (low heat variety)
                ¾ to 1 teaspoon garam masala (adjust to taste)
                1 teaspoon coriander powder (optional)
                12 to 14 cashews
                ¾ teaspoon sugar (optional, to balance the flavors)</ul>
            <li>¾ to 1 teaspoon Kashmiri red chili powder (low heat variety)</li>
            <li>¾ to 1 teaspoon garam masala (adjust to taste)</li>
            <li>1 teaspoon coriander powder (optional)</li>
            <li>12 to 14 cashews</li>
            <li>¾ teaspoon sugar (optional, to balance the flavors)</li>
            <p>5. Saute this onion tomato masala on a low heat for 2 to 3 minutes. It should begin
                to smell good and aromatic. Turn off the stove.</p>
            <p>6. Cool this completely and add to a blender. Pour 1 cup water. Blend this mixture to
                a super smooth puree.
                Tip: To speed up the process, I pour ice cold water to the blender jar first and
                then transfer the warm mixture.</p>
            <p>7. Blend to a very smooth &amp; silky puree. If your blender is not powerful enough
                to make a fine puree, then strain it through a fine strainer to a bowl.</p>
            <h3>Make Paneer Butter Masala</h3>
            <p>8. Heat a pan on a low flame with 1½ tbsp butter. When the butter melts, add all the
                following spices. You can leave them if you don’t have.</p>
            <ul>2 green cardamoms
                1 bay leaf
                ½ inch cinnamon
                3 cloves</ul>
            <li>2 green cardamoms</li>
            <li>1 bay leaf</li>
            <li>½ inch cinnamon</li>
            <li>3 cloves</li>
            <p>9. When the spices begin to sizzle, add 1½ teaspoon ginger garlic paste. Saute for 1
                minute or until you begin to smell it good. The raw smell should go away. Take care
                to cook this on a low to medium heat. Do not burn the paste.</p>
            <p>(Note that you don’t need to add ginger garlic paste if you have used chopped ginger
                and garlic along with onions)</p>
            <p>10. Next pour onion tomato puree. I also added ¼ teaspoon red chili powder for deeper
                color. This is completely optional. Ensure the stove flame is at low else the curry
                begins to splatter.</p>
            <p>11. Immediately pour ½ cup water &amp; mix well to bring it to a gravy consistency.
                If it is too thick you can add little more water.</p>
            <p>12. Cover and cook on a medium flame until the gravy turns thick &amp; flavorful.</p>
            <p>13. When the paneer butter masala gravy is ready, you will see traces of fats over
                the gravy. This is the color you may get. Open the lid and cook until the gravy
                turns thicker. Taste test and add more salt if needed</p>
            <p>14. Make sure the gravy reaches the desired consistency then add 200 to 250 grams
                paneer. Take 1 teaspoon kasuri methi in your palm and crush it between both your
                palms. Then add it to the butter masala. Avoid adding paneer when the gravy is still
                runny.</p>
            <p>15. Stir well. On a low flame cook covered just for 1 to 3 minutes. Cooking for
                longer can make the paneer harder. Add 2 to 3 tablespoons cream and stir. You should
                get this thick creamy texture as you see in the picture below.</p>
            <p>Transfer paneer butter masala to a serving bowl. Garnish with 1 tablespoon cream
                &amp; 1 tablespoon finely chopped coriander leaves. Serve paneer butter masala with
                Jeera rice, chapathi, Paratha, roti, Butter naan or even with plain Basmati Rice.</p>
            <h2>Serving Suggestions</h2>
            <span>Serving Suggestions</span>
            <p>Paneer butter masala is so much flavorful by itself so it can be served with just
                plain basmati rice. Any other kind of non-mushy and grainy rice also goes well. Some
                onion and cucumber slices on the side with lemon wedges will be great.</p>
            <p>However if you choose to have something better than plain rice you can simply make
                jeera rice or ghee rice.</p>
            <p>During their visits to restaurants, most Indians love to eat their paneer butter
                masala with butter naan, tandoori roti or plain kulcha with sliced onions, carrots,
                cucumbers and lemon. At home, we simply eat it with plain soft roti or jeera rice.</p>
            <h2>Pro Tips</h2>
            <span>Pro Tips</span>
            <p>Silky smooth gravy is what makes this dish classic. So blend the cooked onion tomato
                mixture to a very smooth puree. If you do not have a powerful blender then pass the
                puree through a strainer.</p>
            <p>Frying paneer: Usually paneer is added raw while making paneer butter masala. But you
                can also fry it first and then add it to the gravy. But if you are frying it
                inappropriately, then it will turn hard and chewy. Fry them on a medium heat in
                little oil until golden and drop them to a bowl of water. Paneer with absorb the
                water and remain soft. Without this step, simply frying it makes it hard.</p>
            <p>Cream: Avoid cooking paneer butter masala after adding cream. If your cream has no
                added stabilizers, it is most likely to split if you cook the curry after adding
                cream.</p>
            <h2>Ingredients and substitutes</h2>
            <span>Ingredients and substitutes</span>
            <p>Cashews impart a mild sweet &amp; milky flavor to the butter masala. They also
                stabilize and thicken the gravy. So do not skip them. However you can substitute
                them with almonds. Soak them in hot water for an hour, peel off the skin and use
                them here. Substitute nuts with seeds of your choice. More info on this in the
                common questions section below.</p>
            <p>Paneer: If using store bought, ensure you choose one that do not have any additives
                like starch. Usually store bought paneer with added starch becomes rubbery the
                minute it hits the hot curry. It is a good idea to refresh your store bought paneer
                by soaking in hot water for 15 to 20 mins. This step prevents rubbery paneer.</p>
            <p>Paneer can be substituted in this recipe with tofu, quorn, boiled eggs or grilled
                mixed vegetables.</p>
            <p>Onions are the key ingredient in this recipe and is used to naturally sweeten the
                gravy. They also help to balance the tang from the tomatoes. If you prefer to skip
                onions, then balance the tang by adding more cashews or cream.</p>
            <p>Ripe tomatoes not only enhance the color of the paneer butter masala but also add a
                slight tang to the curry. Always use red ripe tomatoes. Avoid them if they are even
                slightly unripe as they alter the flavor of the dish.</p>
            <p>Butter is another important ingredient. If possible use unsalted butter. I feel the
                salted one is not as fresh as the unsalted one. Use fresh and nice smelling butter.
                If you don’t eat butter, then you may use oil or ghee. But your paneer butter masala
                will lack the real flavor of butter.</p>
            <p>Cream: On different occasions, I have made this recipe with fresh cream, whipping
                cream, heavy cream, cooking cream &amp; sterilized cream. All of these are dairy
                creams &amp; work well. If using cooking cream, use 3 tbsps more than mentioned in
                the recipe. If using sterilized cream, whisk the cream in the container with a fork
                until smooth and uniform. Then pour it.</p>
            <h3>Spices for paneer butter masala</h3>
            <p>Garam masala is the key ingredient to flavor up any Indian curry. Not all garam
                masala are same. Unfortunately most store bought garam masala are low in flavor.
                Since they oxidize, their natural flavors diminish. So please use a good one. Also
                adjust the quantity to suit your taste. I use this homemade garam masala.</p>
            <p>Kashmiri red chilli powder imparts that deep color to the dish without making it
                extremely spicy or hot. Avoid using hotter kind. Use any other similar variety that
                is low in heat like byadgi chilli powder or paprika.</p>
            <p>Whole spices can be skipped except for 2 cardamoms added with onions. If you don’t
                have the cardamoms, then simply substitute the whole cardamom pods with ¼ to 1/3
                teaspoon ground cardamom. Add it along with garam masala and not while frying the
                onions.</p>
            <p>Kasuri methi are dried fenugreek leaves and they impart a great unique aroma to the
                dish. If you do not find them just skip as there is no substitute to this. But you
                will miss the flavors of kasuri methi. You can find this easily in any Indian store
                or amazon.</p>
            <h3>How to make one pot dish?</h3>
            <p>Make the entire dish in a steel pot. To make it this way, soak the cashews in hot
                water for 30 mins. Skip all the whole spices in the recipe. To compensate for the
                flavors, add more garam masala if you wish.</p>
            <p>To start with, saute the ginger garlic in butter and oil. Then add the onions. Follow
                the recipe as is till you saute the onion tomato masala. Take the pan off the heat
                &amp; pour water as mentioned in the recipe card.</p>
            <p>Using an immersion blender, blend the ingredients to a smooth puree. Then put back
                the pan on the stove and simmer until the gravy thickens and you see traces of fats
                over the gravy.</p>
            <p>It takes about 10 to 12 mins from the time the curry comes to a rolling boil. But
                simmer the curry &amp; do not cook on high heat as it will splash out of the pot.</p>
            <h2>Instant pot Butter Paneer</h2>
            <span>Instant pot Butter Paneer</span>
            <p>To the instant pot steel insert, add 1 cup cubed onions, 1 ½ cups chopped tomatoes,
                14 cashews, ¾ inch ginger, 3 cloves of garlic and 2 green cardamoms. Pour 1 cup
                water.</p>
            <p>Secure the Instant pot with the lid and position the steam valve to sealing. Press
                pressure cook button and set the timer for 6 mins.</p>
            <p>When the pressure releases, open the lid and remove the rice bowl.</p>
            <p>Using an immersion blender, blend this to a smooth puree. If you don’t have an
                immersion blender, strain the stock/water and set aside. Cool the onion mixture and
                add to a blender. Make a fine puree adding some strained stock/water as needed.</p>
            <p>Add 2 tablespoons butter to the instant pot. Press saute button (low). When the
                butter melts, add ¾ to 1 teaspoon red chilli powder, ¾ to 1 teaspoon garam masala, 1
                teaspoon coriander powder, ¾ teaspoon salt and 1 teaspoon sugar.</p>
            <p>Quickly pour the left over strained water and the onion tomato mixture. If you do not
                own a powerful blender then simply pass the mixture through a sieve/filter.</p>
            <p>Mix everything and add more water if needed to bring it to a gravy consistency. I add
                another half cup water.</p>
            <p>Let it simmer for about 7 to 8 minutes on saute (low). This is a very important step
                for a flavorful paneer butter masala. In between keep stirring to prevent burning.
                Switch between off &amp; saute if the pot becomes too hot &amp; the mixture sticks
                to the steel insert.</p>
            <p>When the gravy is cooked, you will see traces of butter over the curry. Taste test
                and add salt, sugar or more garam masala if needed.</p>
            <p>Ensure the gravy is thick and smooth. Then turn off the Instant pot. Add paneer,
                crushed kasuri methi and cream. Give a good stir and carefully remove the steel
                insert from the instant pot. Be careful as it will be hot.</p>
            <p>Cover the pot with a plate and let it rest for 5 to 10 mins. Garnish paneer butter
                masala with cream and coriander leaves.</p>
            <h3>Instant pot tips for butter paneer</h3>
            <p>For best results, I use a blender to puree my onion tomato masala and pass it through
                a strainer. My immersion blender does not give the same silky smooth texture to the
                paneer butter masala gravy.</p>
            <p>You can also simply cook all the ingredients in a bowl (PIP) in the Instant pot. Cool
                them and blend. Make the curry on the stovetop.</p>
            <p>You can also cook your basmati rice in the instant pot when you pressure cook the
                onion tomato masala. For that add 2 cups basmati rice to a bowl and pour 2 ½ cups
                water (serves 4). Place a trivet in your instant pot and keep the rice bowl over
                that.</p>
            <p>Sometimes I also add 1 tbsp ghee, some roasted cumin and other whole spices to the
                basmati rice to make jeera rice. You can check the quantity of spices on this jeera
                rice post.</p>
            <h2>Faqs</h2>
            <span>Faqs</span>
            <p>It is a high calorie dish so enjoy this occasionally &amp; moderately. Serve it with
                healthier options like whole wheat roti, chapatti, phulka, tandoori roti or steamed
                rice.</p>
            <p>It is just another name for paneer butter masala. Since paneer is cooked in a buttery
                masala (masala that is cooked in butter) it is also called as butter paneer.</p>
            <p>Unfortunately more often milk curdles when cooked with acidic ingredients like
                tomatoes. So instead use more cashews in the recipe and skip cream.</p>
            <p>To get the exact taste of cream, substitute it with cashew cream. To make your own,
                soak 15 cashew nuts in warm water for an hour and blend it until creamy, smooth and
                thick. Add this at the last step after you turn off the stove.</p>
            <p>Paneer butter masala is essentially cooked in butter, has a smooth silky curry to
                which raw paneer is added. But paneer tikka masala is made with grilled paneer and
                is predominantly spicy and has some texture in the curry.</p>
            <p>Yes you can fry it in a tablespoon of oil until golden &amp; drop them to a bowl of
                water. This helps them to remain soft. But frying won’t add any taste to the paneer.</p>
            <p>Overcooking paneer makes it rubbery. Just add it to hot gravy and cook no further.
                Keep the pan covered so the paneer cooks in the residual heat. Also do not leave
                your paneer curry on the hot burner as it continues to cook.</p>
            <h3>Common questions</h3>
            <p>How to make paneer butter masala ahead?</p>
            <p>Make the gravy or curry base without cream. Cool it completely. Refrigerate or freeze
                it in glass containers. Reheat it until bubbling hot, then add paneer. Cook for 2
                mins and add cream.</p>
            <p>How to make this recipe vegan?</p>
            <p>This recipe can be made vegan easily by substituting paneer with extra firm tofu or
                any grilled veggies. Use vegan butter &amp; vegan cream for butter and cream
                substitutes.</p>
            <p>Can I use this recipe to make butter chicken?</p>
            <p>You can use the sauce for butter chicken, but the spice levels I use for meat recipes
                is higher. I do have separate recipes, you can these Butter Chicken and Chicken
                Butter Masala.</p>
            <p>Why are nuts &amp; seeds used in paneer curry?</p>
            <p>There are a lot of paneer curries where apart from cashews even almonds, magaz seeds
                (melon seeds) and poppy seeds are used. All of these serve the same purpose. They
                not only impart a creamy texture to the curry but also tones down the heat by adding
                a milky aroma to the dish.</p>
            <p>Apart from this nuts &amp; seeds also work as a stabilizer there by not splitting or
                curdling the curry in which tomatoes and dairy are used.</p>
            <p>What is the best substitute for nuts &amp; how to use?</p>
            <p>There are a lot of people who cannot eat nuts due to allergies. For them a good
                substitute is poppy seeds, hulled white sesame seeds and sunflower seeds. I have
                tried with the first 2 options but a few readers have made this sunflower seeds too.</p>
            <p>Soak these in warm water for 3 to 4 hours and then discard the water. Blend them with
                fresh water in a nut grinder or a chutney grinder until very smooth. Pass it through
                a sieve along with onion tomato puree.</p>
            <h3>Are paneer butter masala &amp; paneer makhani same?</h3>
            <p>No, Just like Chicken butter masala and Chicken makhani (Butter chicken) are
                different &amp; not the same, even paneer butter masala and paneer makhani are
                different.</p>
            <p>Though both are cooked in butter with similar ingredients they are not the same. But
                many restaurants use the terms interchangeably.</p>
            <p>Paneer butter masala is a restaurant derived dish and there is no one particular way
                it is made across India. Each restaurant follows their own method &amp; a set of
                ingredients.</p>
            <p>Example – onions, poppy seeds, melon seeds, cream etc. That’s why no 2 restaurants
                serve the same tasting paneer butter masala.</p>
            <p>Paneer makhani on the other hand is a dish made with specific ingredients tomatoes,
                cashews and cream. It does not make use of ingredients like onions, poppy seeds or
                melon seeds. You can check the recipe of Paneer makhani here.</p>
            <p>Related Recipes</p>
            <h3>Paneer Pasanda Re...</h3>
            <h3>Paneer Curry Reci...</h3>
            <h3>Paneer Recipes</h3>
            <h3>Kadai Paneer Reci...</h3>
            <h3>Paneer Tikka Masa...</h3>
            <h3>Malai Kofta Recip...</h3>
            <h2>Recipe Card</h2>
            <span>Recipe Card</span>
            <h2>PANEER BUTTER MASALA RECIPE</h2>
            <span>This paneer butter masala is a curry lover’s dream!! Soft paneer dunked in a
                creamy, silky, super flavorful and delicious curry. My easy paneer recipe will help
                you make the best butter paneer that tastes better than anything from a restaurant.
                Make this once, I am sure you will never order it in a restaurant. Serve it with
                butter naan, roti or Basmati rice.</span>
            <p>For best results follow the step-by-step photos above the recipe card</p>
            <span>Prep Time</span>
            <span>15
                minutes
                minutes</span>
            <span>15
                minutes</span>
            <span>minutes</span>
            <span>minutes</span>
            <span>Cook Time</span>
            <span>30
                minutes
                minutes</span>
            <span>30
                minutes</span>
            <span>minutes</span>
            <span>minutes</span>
            <span>Total Time</span>
            <span>40
                minutes
                minutes</span>
            <span>40
                minutes</span>
            <span>minutes</span>
            <span>minutes</span>
            <span>Servings</span>
            <span>4</span>
            <span>Author</span>
            <span>Swasthi</span>
            <h3>INGREDIENTS (US CUP = 240ML )</h3>
            <ul>▢
                1 tablespoon oil
                ▢
                2 green cardamoms (or ¼ to ⅓ tsp ground cardamom, elaichi)
                ▢
                1 cup onions cubed, 3 medium
                ▢
                1½ to 2 cups tomatoes finely chopped (3 large)
                ▢
                ¾ teaspoon salt (adjust to taste)
                ▢
                ¾ teaspoon sugar (optional)
                ▢
                12 to 14 cashew nuts (or 12 almonds)
                ▢
                ¾ to 1 teaspoon Kashmiri red chilli powder (or paprika)(adjust for best color)
                ▢
                ¾ to 1 teaspoon garam masala powder (adjust to taste)
                ▢
                1 teaspoon coriander powder (daniya powder) (optional)
                ▢
                1 cup water (to blend)</ul>
            <li>▢
                1 tablespoon oil</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>1</span>
            <span>tablespoon</span>
            <span>oil</span>
            <li>▢
                2 green cardamoms (or ¼ to ⅓ tsp ground cardamom, elaichi)</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>2</span>
            <span>green cardamoms</span>
            <span>(or ¼ to ⅓ tsp ground cardamom, elaichi)</span>
            <li>▢
                1 cup onions cubed, 3 medium</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>1</span>
            <span>cup</span>
            <span>onions</span>
            <span>cubed, 3 medium</span>
            <li>▢
                1½ to 2 cups tomatoes finely chopped (3 large)</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>1½ to 2</span>
            <span>cups</span>
            <span>tomatoes</span>
            <span>finely chopped (3 large)</span>
            <li>▢
                ¾ teaspoon salt (adjust to taste)</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>¾</span>
            <span>teaspoon</span>
            <span>salt</span>
            <span>(adjust to taste)</span>
            <li>▢
                ¾ teaspoon sugar (optional)</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>¾</span>
            <span>teaspoon</span>
            <span>sugar</span>
            <span>(optional)</span>
            <li>▢
                12 to 14 cashew nuts (or 12 almonds)</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>12 to 14</span>
            <span>cashew nuts</span>
            <span>(or 12 almonds)</span>
            <li>▢
                ¾ to 1 teaspoon Kashmiri red chilli powder (or paprika)(adjust for best color)</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>¾ to 1</span>
            <span>teaspoon</span>
            <span>Kashmiri red chilli powder</span>
            <span>(or paprika)(adjust for best color)</span>
            <li>▢
                ¾ to 1 teaspoon garam masala powder (adjust to taste)</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>¾ to 1</span>
            <span>teaspoon</span>
            <span>garam masala</span>
            <span>powder (adjust to taste)</span>
            <li>▢
                1 teaspoon coriander powder (daniya powder) (optional)</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>1</span>
            <span>teaspoon</span>
            <span>coriander powder</span>
            <span>(daniya powder) (optional)</span>
            <li>▢
                1 cup water (to blend)</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>1</span>
            <span>cup</span>
            <span>water</span>
            <span>(to blend)</span>
            <ul>▢
                1 small bay leaf (tej patta)
                ▢
                ½ inch cinnamon piece (dalchini) (optional)
                ▢
                2 green cardamom (elaichi) (optional)
                ▢
                3 cloves (laung) (optional)</ul>
            <li>▢
                1 small bay leaf (tej patta)</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>1</span>
            <span>small</span>
            <span>bay leaf</span>
            <span>(tej patta)</span>
            <li>▢
                ½ inch cinnamon piece (dalchini) (optional)</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>½</span>
            <span>inch</span>
            <span>cinnamon piece</span>
            <span>(dalchini) (optional)</span>
            <li>▢
                2 green cardamom (elaichi) (optional)</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>2</span>
            <span>green cardamom</span>
            <span>(elaichi) (optional)</span>
            <li>▢
                3 cloves (laung) (optional)</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>3</span>
            <span>cloves</span>
            <span>(laung) (optional)</span>
            <ul>▢
                1½ to 2 tablespoon Butter
                ▢
                1½ teaspoon ginger garlic paste (or ¾ inch ginger, 3 medium garlic cloves, refer
                notes)
                ▢
                ½ cup water (adjust as required, to cook the gravy)
                ▢
                200 to 250 grams paneer (2 heaped cups diced)
                ▢
                1 teaspoon kasuri methi (dried fenugreek leaves)
                ▢
                3 tablespoon cream (heavy cream, whipping cream or cooking cream)
                ▢
                2 tablespoon coriander leaves (cilantro finely chopped) (for garnish)</ul>
            <li>▢
                1½ to 2 tablespoon Butter</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>1½ to 2</span>
            <span>tablespoon</span>
            <span>Butter</span>
            <li>▢
                1½ teaspoon ginger garlic paste (or ¾ inch ginger, 3 medium garlic cloves, refer
                notes)</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>1½</span>
            <span>teaspoon</span>
            <span>ginger garlic paste</span>
            <span>(or ¾ inch ginger, 3 medium garlic cloves, refer notes)</span>
            <li>▢
                ½ cup water (adjust as required, to cook the gravy)</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>½</span>
            <span>cup</span>
            <span>water</span>
            <span>(adjust as required, to cook the gravy)</span>
            <li>▢
                200 to 250 grams paneer (2 heaped cups diced)</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>200 to 250</span>
            <span>grams</span>
            <span>paneer</span>
            <span>(2 heaped cups diced)</span>
            <li>▢
                1 teaspoon kasuri methi (dried fenugreek leaves)</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>1</span>
            <span>teaspoon</span>
            <span>kasuri methi</span>
            <span>(dried fenugreek leaves)</span>
            <li>▢
                3 tablespoon cream (heavy cream, whipping cream or cooking cream)</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>3</span>
            <span>tablespoon</span>
            <span>cream</span>
            <span>(heavy cream, whipping cream or cooking cream)</span>
            <li>▢
                2 tablespoon coriander leaves (cilantro finely chopped) (for garnish)</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>2</span>
            <span>tablespoon</span>
            <span>coriander leaves</span>
            <span>(cilantro finely chopped) (for garnish)</span>
            <h3>INSTRUCTIONS</h3>
            <ul>▢
                Heat oil in a pan. Add green cardamoms &amp; onions. Stir fry until they turn
                transparent to light pink. (If you do not have ginger garlic paste for this recipe,
                you may add chopped ginger and garlic along with onions)
                ▢
                Next add tomatoes &amp; salt. Saute for 3 minutes. Cover and cook till the onion
                &amp; tomatoes turn soft &amp; completely mushy.
                ▢
                Add garam masala, coriander powder, cashew nuts, red chili powder &amp; sugar
                (optional).
                ▢
                Stir fry this till the onion tomato masala turns aromatic. This takes 2 to 3
                minutes.
                ▢
                Turn off the stove &amp; cool this completely.
                ▢
                Transfer to a blender &amp; pour water. Blend to a really silky smooth puree. If it
                is not smooth, filter it through a strainer to another bowl. Set this aside.</ul>
            <li>▢
                Heat oil in a pan. Add green cardamoms &amp; onions. Stir fry until they turn
                transparent to light pink. (If you do not have ginger garlic paste for this recipe,
                you may add chopped ginger and garlic along with onions)</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>Heat oil in a pan. Add green cardamoms &amp; onions. Stir fry until they turn
                transparent to light pink. (If you do not have ginger garlic paste for this recipe,
                you may add chopped ginger and garlic along with onions)</span>
            <li>▢
                Next add tomatoes &amp; salt. Saute for 3 minutes. Cover and cook till the onion
                &amp; tomatoes turn soft &amp; completely mushy.</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>Next add tomatoes &amp; salt. Saute for 3 minutes. Cover and cook till the onion
                &amp; tomatoes turn soft &amp; completely mushy.</span>
            <li>▢
                Add garam masala, coriander powder, cashew nuts, red chili powder &amp; sugar
                (optional).</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>Add garam masala, coriander powder, cashew nuts, red chili powder &amp; sugar
                (optional).</span>
            <li>▢
                Stir fry this till the onion tomato masala turns aromatic. This takes 2 to 3
                minutes.</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>Stir fry this till the onion tomato masala turns aromatic. This takes 2 to 3
                minutes.</span>
            <li>▢
                Turn off the stove &amp; cool this completely.</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>Turn off the stove &amp; cool this completely.</span>
            <li>▢
                Transfer to a blender &amp; pour water. Blend to a really silky smooth puree. If it
                is not smooth, filter it through a strainer to another bowl. Set this aside.</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>Transfer to a blender &amp; pour water. Blend to a really silky smooth puree. If
                it is not smooth, filter it through a strainer to another bowl. Set this aside.</span>
            <ul>▢
                Heat butter in the same pan. Optional – When the butter melts, add cinnamon, cloves,
                green cardamoms &amp; bay leaf.
                ▢
                Reduce the flame to low, saute ginger garlic paste for a minute until it smells
                aromatic.
                ▢
                Stir in the blended onion tomato puree. Taste test your puree &amp; optionally you
                may add more red chili powder for a deeper color.
                ▢
                Pour more water &amp; mix well. Bring it to a rolling boil. Reduce the heat to
                medium and cook covered until the gravy cooks down to a thicker consistency. Keep
                stirring every few minutes.
                ▢
                You know the gravy is done when it turns thick and traces of fat is visible on the
                gravy. Taste test and add more salt or garam masala if needed.
                ▢
                Lower the flame completely, add cubed paneer. Take kasuri methi to your palm and
                crush it in between your palms. Sprinkle this.
                ▢
                Mix &amp; cook covered on a low heat for 2 minutes. Turn off and pour cream (save
                some for garnish) &amp; stir.
                ▢
                Transfer paneer butter masala to a serving bowl. Garnish with more cream &amp;
                chopped coriander leaves. Serve this with butter naan , Basmati rice or jeera rice.</ul>
            <li>▢
                Heat butter in the same pan. Optional – When the butter melts, add cinnamon, cloves,
                green cardamoms &amp; bay leaf.</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>Heat butter in the same pan. Optional – When the butter melts, add cinnamon,
                cloves, green cardamoms &amp; bay leaf.</span>
            <li>▢
                Reduce the flame to low, saute ginger garlic paste for a minute until it smells
                aromatic.</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>Reduce the flame to low, saute ginger garlic paste for a minute until it smells
                aromatic.</span>
            <li>▢
                Stir in the blended onion tomato puree. Taste test your puree &amp; optionally you
                may add more red chili powder for a deeper color.</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>Stir in the blended onion tomato puree. Taste test your puree &amp; optionally you
                may add more red chili powder for a deeper color.</span>
            <li>▢
                Pour more water &amp; mix well. Bring it to a rolling boil. Reduce the heat to
                medium and cook covered until the gravy cooks down to a thicker consistency. Keep
                stirring every few minutes.</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>Pour more water &amp; mix well. Bring it to a rolling boil. Reduce the heat to
                medium and cook covered until the gravy cooks down to a thicker consistency. Keep
                stirring every few minutes.</span>
            <li>▢
                You know the gravy is done when it turns thick and traces of fat is visible on the
                gravy. Taste test and add more salt or garam masala if needed.</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>You know the gravy is done when it turns thick and traces of fat is visible on the
                gravy. Taste test and add more salt or garam masala if needed.</span>
            <li>▢
                Lower the flame completely, add cubed paneer. Take kasuri methi to your palm and
                crush it in between your palms. Sprinkle this.</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>Lower the flame completely, add cubed paneer. Take kasuri methi to your palm and
                crush it in between your palms. Sprinkle this.</span>
            <li>▢
                Mix &amp; cook covered on a low heat for 2 minutes. Turn off and pour cream (save
                some for garnish) &amp; stir.</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>Mix &amp; cook covered on a low heat for 2 minutes. Turn off and pour cream (save
                some for garnish) &amp; stir.</span>
            <li>▢
                Transfer paneer butter masala to a serving bowl. Garnish with more cream &amp;
                chopped coriander leaves. Serve this with butter naan , Basmati rice or jeera rice.</li>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>▢</span>
            <span>Transfer paneer butter masala to a serving bowl. Garnish with more cream &amp;
                chopped coriander leaves. Serve this with butter naan , Basmati rice or jeera rice.</span>
            <h3>NOTES</h3>
            <ul>Ginger Garlic: If you do not have ginger garlic paste, you can saute chopped ginger
                garlic along with the onions.
                Prep Time: To cut down the cooking time, chop the onions and begin to cook right
                away. Prepare the rest (ginger, garlic, tomatoes etc) as you cook. This saves a lot
                of time.
                Whole spices can be skipped except for 2 cardamoms to be added to onions while
                sautéing. You can substitute those 2 cardamoms with ¼ to 1/3 teaspoon ground
                cardamom. Add it along with the garam masala and not while frying the onions.
                Substitute paneer with tofu, quorn, boiled eggs or grilled veggies. If using quorn,
                add it to the pan along with water.
                Use a good garam masala that is fragrant. Every brand is different so adjust the
                quantity as needed until you are happy with the flavors.
                Use fresh red ripe tomatoes. Avoid using unripe tomatoes as the flavour will be
                different. You can use the same amount of crushed tomatoes or bottled tomato puree.
                Cashews can be substituted with almonds. Soak the almonds in hot water for 30 mins.
                Peel the skin and use them in the recipe. Taste test the nuts before using just to
                ensure they are not rancid.
                There is no substitute for kasuri methi (dried fenugreek leaves). You may skip them
                but will miss the distinct flavors.
                Prefer unsalted butter over salted as unsalted is fresher and better in flavour.
                Substitute cream with 15 cashews. Soak the raw cashew nuts in ¼ cup warm water for
                30 minutes. Add them to a small grinder and blend until smooth, creamy and uniform.
                Add more water if needed to bring it to consistency. Add this at the last step for
                garnishing.
                You need a powerful blender to blend the onions tomato mixture to a very smooth
                puree. Silky smooth gravy is what makes this butter paneer classic. If you do not
                have a powerful blender then pass the puree through a strainer. You can blend the
                leftover coarse mixture again with little water.
                If making for kids, reduce the chilli powder to half teaspoon. Or add more cream to
                the kids’ servings to tone down the heat.
                You can skip using garlic and onion and make a no onion no garlic paneer butter
                masala recipe. But balance the tang by adding more cashews and more cream.</ul>
            <li>Ginger Garlic: If you do not have ginger garlic paste, you can saute chopped ginger
                garlic along with the onions.</li>
            <li>Prep Time: To cut down the cooking time, chop the onions and begin to cook right
                away. Prepare the rest (ginger, garlic, tomatoes etc) as you cook. This saves a lot
                of time.</li>
            <li>Whole spices can be skipped except for 2 cardamoms to be added to onions while
                sautéing. You can substitute those 2 cardamoms with ¼ to 1/3 teaspoon ground
                cardamom. Add it along with the garam masala and not while frying the onions.</li>
            <li>Substitute paneer with tofu, quorn, boiled eggs or grilled veggies. If using quorn,
                add it to the pan along with water.</li>
            <li>Use a good garam masala that is fragrant. Every brand is different so adjust the
                quantity as needed until you are happy with the flavors.</li>
            <li>Use fresh red ripe tomatoes. Avoid using unripe tomatoes as the flavour will be
                different. You can use the same amount of crushed tomatoes or bottled tomato puree.</li>
            <li>Cashews can be substituted with almonds. Soak the almonds in hot water for 30 mins.
                Peel the skin and use them in the recipe. Taste test the nuts before using just to
                ensure they are not rancid.</li>
            <li>There is no substitute for kasuri methi (dried fenugreek leaves). You may skip them
                but will miss the distinct flavors.</li>
            <li>Prefer unsalted butter over salted as unsalted is fresher and better in flavour.</li>
            <li>Substitute cream with 15 cashews. Soak the raw cashew nuts in ¼ cup warm water for
                30 minutes. Add them to a small grinder and blend until smooth, creamy and uniform.
                Add more water if needed to bring it to consistency. Add this at the last step for
                garnishing.</li>
            <li>You need a powerful blender to blend the onions tomato mixture to a very smooth
                puree. Silky smooth gravy is what makes this butter paneer classic. If you do not
                have a powerful blender then pass the puree through a strainer. You can blend the
                leftover coarse mixture again with little water.</li>
            <li>If making for kids, reduce the chilli powder to half teaspoon. Or add more cream to
                the kids’ servings to tone down the heat.</li>
            <li>You can skip using garlic and onion and make a no onion no garlic paneer butter
                masala recipe. But balance the tang by adding more cashews and more cream.</li>
            <p>Alternative quantities provided in the recipe card are for 1x only, original recipe.</p>
            <p>For best results follow my detailed step-by-step photo instructions and tips above
                the recipe card.</p>
            <h3>VIDEO</h3>
            <h3>NUTRITION INFO (estimation only)</h3>
            <span>Calories 347</span>
            <span>Calories from Fat 261</span>
            <span>% Daily Value*</span>
            <span>Fat 29g</span>
            <span>45%</span>
            <span>Saturated Fat 15g</span>
            <span>94%</span>
            <span>Cholesterol 68mg</span>
            <span>23%</span>
            <span>Sodium 77mg</span>
            <span>3%</span>
            <span>Potassium 274mg</span>
            <span>8%</span>
            <span>Carbohydrates 11g</span>
            <span>4%</span>
            <span>Fiber 2g</span>
            <span>8%</span>
            <span>Sugar 4g</span>
            <span>4%</span>
            <span>Protein 10g</span>
            <span>20%</span>
            <span>Vitamin A 1025IU</span>
            <span>21%</span>
            <span>Vitamin C 17.6mg</span>
            <span>21%</span>
            <span>Calcium 349mg</span>
            <span>35%</span>
            <span>Iron 1.2mg</span>
            <span>7%</span>
            <span>Tried this recipe?
                Mention @SwasthisRecipes or tag #swasthisrecipes!</span>
            <span>Tried this recipe?</span>
            <span>Mention @SwasthisRecipes or tag #swasthisrecipes!</span>
            <p>© Swasthi’s Recipes</p>
            <p>This recipe was first published in November 2014. Updated &amp; republished in
                December 2020 with lots of tips, substitutes &amp; instant pot instructions.</p>
            <h2>About Swasthi</h2>
            <p>I’m Swasthi Shreekanth, the recipe developer, food photographer &amp; food writer
                behind Swasthi’s Recipes. My aim is to help you cook great Indian food with my
                time-tested recipes. After 2 decades of experience in practical Indian cooking I
                started this blog to help people cook better &amp; more often at home. Whether you
                are a novice or an experienced cook I am sure Swasthi’s Recipes will assist you to
                enhance your cooking skills. More about me</p>
            <p>Follow Swasthi’s Recipes</p>
            <ul>Facebook
                Twitter
                Instagram
                Pinterest
                YouTube</ul>
            <li>Facebook</li>
            <span>Facebook</span>
            <li>Twitter</li>
            <span>Twitter</span>
            <li>Instagram</li>
            <span>Instagram</span>
            <li>Pinterest</li>
            <span>Pinterest</span>
            <li>YouTube</li>
            <span>YouTube</span>
            <span>*</span>
            <h2>Post navigation</h2>
            <h3>Comments</h3>
            <p>Outstanding, loved it. Thank you!</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Have been cooking paneer for several years now but made it with this recipe and it
                was just outstanding! The taste, the creaminess and the simple aspect of submerging
                the paneer cubes for 20min in hot water was a game changer.
                Thank you for this recipe!</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Absolutely delicious and really easy to make! I used tofu instead of paneer (paneer
                is impossible to get in Spain) and it worked out perfectly. Many thanks!</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Wow Wow Wow! I was looking for a good recipe for paneer. This is it!! Delicious
                comfort food for fall. Thank you for sharing! I’ve already forwarded your recipe to
                many friends!!</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>This was INCREDIBLE! I usually struggle with Indian dishes, but this was easy to
                follow and simply delicious. Definitely one I will be repeating!</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Hi Swasthi,
                Love your recipes n this one is my favourite.
                My kids love paneer butter masala recipe of yours as it tastes exactly like
                resturant style.
                Though this is my first comment I have been ur follower for many years.</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Hi Gayathri,
                Thank you so much! That makes me happy!</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Not going to lie, I just thought this was a curry recipe, how wrong was I.
                It is a delicious recipe. We replace the heavy cream with coconut milk, but
                otherwise it’s quite perfect.
                Thank you so much for sharing it’s now our family favourite</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Thank you for this wonderful recipe, I’ve made it dozens of times and its it’s my
                go-to dish for family meals!
                In the notes you can make it ahead of time, just leaving out the cream, I presume,
                it would last a couple of days in fridge?</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Hi Aimee,
                So happy to know that! It lasts for 4 to 5 days in the refrigerator without cream. A
                lot of times I also put the leftovers with the cream included the refrigerator and
                reheat after 3 days. It does not split but still I would like to warn others it may.
                Thank you!</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Hello Swasthi,
                I’m following your blog since the lockdown and this recipe is one of our favorite
                dishes. My friends say I make the best paneer butter masala. How can I adjust this
                recipe to make more gravy. I try to make 5 servings and it gives me spices and many
                ingredients in fractions &amp; decimals. When I 2x the recipe I have no issues. But
                1x with a little more gravy is what we prefer. My growing children seem to be
                enjoying more gravy. Please help. Any inputs are appreciated.</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Hi Ashwini,
                Thank you so much! That makes me very happy! I have the latest version of this
                recipe which I use at home for my family. It makes more sauce too. I will try to
                update it here in a couple of days. Hope that helps.</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Wonderful recipe. My family loved it.
                Thank you. I always follow your recipes.
                Very tasty recipe. I make this often.</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Thank you R. Menon. Glad you like the recipes.</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Made tonight and it was quite good, but I may have misunderstood a step (though I
                read through several times). After making the tomato mixture, you melt butter in the
                pan and add the whole spices (cloves, bay leaf, cardamom, cinnamon stick), I assumed
                that you remove the whole spices after they become aromatic and before you add the
                tomato puree back to the pan? Is that right? I would have loved to leave the whole
                spices in longer while it thickened but I don’t know how you would find them to
                remove them (especially the clove and cardamom). Thanks for clarifying</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Hey Sam,
                Missed replying you. We remove the spices while serving as they continue to infuse
                flavors even after cooking. I have a complete step by step photo guide and video on
                every recipe. When in doubt, please take a look at those. Hope this helps</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Amazing despite not adding cream it was really tasty. Thanks Swasthi I love your
                recipes they are very clearly explained.</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>So glad you like it Mini. Thank you so much!</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Made this for my MIL who loves paneer butter masala and she was blown away. Made it
                for the first time following your recipe and it was a hit. Your blog is a lifesaver
                for so many of us clueless cooks out there. Thank you Swasthi.</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Yamuna, so happy to know your MIL liked the meal. Thank you so much for sharing back
                how the food turned out.
                🙂</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Thank you! This paneer butter masala is outstanding.</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>So glad you like it Catherine. Thank you</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>I’m going to be honest, after I made this dish I myself wasn’t impressed entirely
                because I had used ghee instead of butter (which I didn’t have on hand) but my
                Indian roommate and my daughter who never eats curries and hates Indian food – LOVED
                IT!!! My Indian roommate said this was the best paneer butter masala she has ever
                had. My daughter asked me to save the remaining portion (I doubled the batch) for
                her! I’m over the moon grateful for this recipe and we will be making this our
                staple paneer butter masala recipe! Thank you precious Lady!</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Jenna, Thank you so much for sharing back how it turned out. So happy to read this!
                🙂</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>AMAZING. As a life long vegetarian, it’s tough to find a recipe that you can easily
                throw into the repertoire of regular meals, but this one definitely is a new
                standard. I like to throw in a few spicy peppers to up the heat, but the best part
                was when the Indian grocery I frequent asked why I keep buying so much paneer. They
                had be bring in a plate to sample, and were dumbfounded that a white dude could bust
                out something so authentic tasting. Absolutely love this recipe, and so does anyone
                who tries it</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Nolan, Wow! That’s awesome!
                So happy to read your paneer butter masala turns out so good. Thank you so much for
                sharing back.</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Thank you for sharing your recipes and your expertise! This one is so fantastic! And
                with the naan…so good. Serving this makes me look good, that’s for sure 🙂 And
                tonight, we had a vegetarian for dinner, so I had to sub the cashews with chick
                peas, and it actually worked. I was so happy.</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>So glad to know Liz. Thanks for sharing back about chickpeas. This is surely going to
                help others who want to avoid nuts.</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>I tried this as home… amazing ?</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Thanks Sinchita</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Very well explained. It was a hit in the 1st attempt itself</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Thanks Sabrina. Glad it was a hit</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Excellent recipe!! I followed to the last tee. It was a hit! My kids enjoyed it. I
                definitely will recommend this recipe to all my friends.</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Thank you so much Premila. Glad your kids’ enjoyed it!</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>I only use your recipes! The results I get are amazing – so flavorful! I get asked by
                my Indian friends how I cook Indian so well – i send them your weblink!
                I made your paneer butter masala recipe. The gravy separated. What did I do wrong?</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <p>Thanks for trying Nancy. Happy to know the recipes work well for you. Do you mean the
                gravy split? Did you use milk in the recipe? Because there is no ingredient that can
                split the gravy. We add cream only at the end. If you tell me what changes you made
                to the recipe I can suggest you</p>
            <span>Reply</span>
            <h2>Popular Recipes</h2>
            <h2>Categories</h2>
            <h2>Sweets</h2>
            <h2>Collection</h2>
            <p>© 2023 Swasthi's Recipes</p>
        </blogContent>
    </recipe>
</recipes>